<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Edited: 14 October 2013 16:10:03 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 14:51:56 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 14:30:54 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 09 October 2013 15:41:48 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 30 September 2013 16:33:21 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 September 2013 11:42:55 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 September 2013 11:29:19 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 September 2013 10:24:34 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 11:39:06 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 11:36:48 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 10:25:22 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 10:16:45 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 08:42:21 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 08:40:05 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 08:37:56 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 08:34:10 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 July 2013 16:03:53 by duncanr--><framework>
   <framework_title>Writing a Critical Evaluation</framework_title>
   <framework_intro>
      <para><![CDATA[]]>Here is a framework to help you write a critical evaluation. There are spaces for you to add your own text.<![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br></para>
   </framework_intro>
   <guided_tour>
      <step label="What is a critical evaluation?">
         <commentary>
            <para><![CDATA[]]>Almost all student writing in any discipline will involve an element of critical evaluation. The purpose of critical evaluation is to show your ability to assess the merits of, for example, a policy document, the results of an experimental study, a legal case report, a business environment or a company, a teaching observation or whatever the central topic of your writing is.</para>
            <para><![CDATA[]]><?xm-replace_text?></para>
            <para><![CDATA[]]>Evaluation involves highlighting the positive and negative aspects of the focus of your discussion, as well as the arguments presented in favour of these aspects. It is part of constructing a viewpoint or an argument which is objective and informed by further reading or experimental study.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="What are the main features?">
         <commentary>
            <para><![CDATA[]]>Critical evaluation not only addresses the negative or weak points of a theory/method/result, but points out the positive aspects too.</para>
            <para><![CDATA[]]><?xm-replace_text?></para>
            <para><![CDATA[]]>Evaluation needs to be accompanied by a rationale or justification, so ensure you provide evidence for your evaluations.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="How is it structured?" para_ids="5,6,22,23,47,48">
         <commentary>
            <para><![CDATA[]]>The structure of your critical evaluation will depend on the topic you are writing about.</para>
            <para><![CDATA[]]><?xm-replace_text?></para>
            <para><![CDATA[]]>The model text is from the discipline of engineering. The text contains three parts of a longer research report—the introduction, a discussion of results, and recommendations. All of these sections display critical evaluation.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at the Introduction " para_ids="5,6,7">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="8"><![CDATA[]]>The writer introduces the topic.</para>
            <para showme="9"><![CDATA[]]>Then the aim of the study is stated.</para>
            <para showme="10,11,12,13,14"><![CDATA[]]>The writer then introduces the methodology and provides an evaluation of the method.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at the Analysis " para_ids="22,23,24">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="25"><![CDATA[]]>This section begins with an introductory evaluation of the results.</para>
            <para showme="26,27,28,29"><![CDATA[]]>Then the results are presented and evaluated in two sections.</para>
            <para showme="30"><![CDATA[]]>The writer then discusses and evaluates the main point on ‘conflict’.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at Recommendations" para_ids="47,48,49">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="50"><![CDATA[]]>The writer discusses the recommendations.</para>
            <para showme="51"><![CDATA[]]>Then an evaluation of the methodology used in the study is provided.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="16,32,53">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="17,19,34,35,37,39,41,42,44,58"><![CDATA[]]>Phrases which express the writer's opinion/evaluation</para>
            <para showme="18,20,33,43,62"><![CDATA[]]>Evaluative adjectives</para>
            <para showme="36,38,40,45,54,55,56,57,59,60,61"><![CDATA[]]>Phrases which indicate the writer is providing a recommendation, sometimes with the pronoun ‘I’</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
   </guided_tour>
   <practice_rubric>
      <planning>
         <checklist>
            <point help="critical_analysis1.xml">Think about the positive and negative points of what you are going to write on.<![CDATA[
]]>Think about the arguments presented in favour of these aspects.</point>
            <point>Decide if you need to do any further reading or experimental study.</point>
            <point help="critical_analysis2.xml">Collect together the evidence you need to support your evaluations.</point>
            <point help="critical_analysis3.xml">Decide on a suitable organization of your ideas.</point>
            <point>Make some notes and organize them into the plan.</point>
         </checklist>
      </planning>
      <vocab>
         <checklist>
            <point help="academic_language.xml">Use academic language.</point>
            <point help="critical_analysis4.xml">Language Bank: evaluating ideas/theories/arguments</point>
            <point help="critical_analysis5.xml">Language Bank: evaluating methods</point>
            <point help="critical_analysis9.xml">Language Bank: critical evaluation</point>
            <point help="critical_analysis10.xml">Language Bank: giving opinions using impersonal language</point>
            <point help="critical_analysis6.xml">Language Bank: making recommendations on methods, theories/ideas, results</point>
         </checklist>
      </vocab>
      <writing>
         <checklist>
            <point help="critical_analysis7.xml">Evaluative adjectives</point>
            <point help="critical_analysis8.xml">Grammar focus: pronouns</point>
         </checklist>
      </writing>
      <checking>
         <checklist>
            <point>Have I addressed both the negative and the positive aspects of the theory/method/result I am discussing?</point>
            <point>Have I provided good evidence for my evaluation?</point>
            <point>Have I used appropriate language to evaluate and make recommendations?</point>
            <point>Have I used evaluative adjectives?</point>
            <point>Have I avoided using ‘I’ too much?</point>
            <point>Does my work follow a clear structure?</point>
            <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar, spelling and punctuation?</point>
         </checklist>
      </checking>
   </practice_rubric>
   <paragraphs>
      <paragraph eid="1">
         <name eid="2">Writing a Critical Evaluation</name>
         <desc eid="3">The purpose of critical evaluation is to show your ability to assess the merits of, for example, a policy document, the results of an experimental study, a legal case report, a business environment or a company, a teaching observation, etc.</desc>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="4">
         <name eid="5">Introduction</name>
         <desc eid="6">Introduce the topic.<![CDATA[</br>
]]>State the aim of the study.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type your Introduction here." eid="7">
            <para prompt="Type your Introduction here." eid="7"><![CDATA[]]>Introduction<![CDATA[
]]><p><extra_info eid="8">This assignment deals with the analysis of one aspect of the suspension set-up of the formula student single-seater race car.</extra_info> 
               <extra_info eid="9">The aim of the assignment is to determine how the suspension performance will change if the suspension geometry is altered.</extra_info> 
               <extra_info eid="10">By modeling one area of the suspension … [describes the methodology and provides a rationale for the method], I chose to investigate the front suspension set-up of the car and, in particular, decided to investigate:</extra_info> </p><![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="11"><br></br>How changing the vertical position of the upper pickup points would affect camber compensation and the lateral position of the roll centre during roll.</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="12"><br></br><br></br>I chose to change position of the upper pickup points of the suspension by:</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="13"><br></br><br></br>+20 mm, +10 mm, -20 mm, -10 mm from the original position, as I consider this to be a fairly realistic range of changes that would be possible to make.</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="14"><br></br><br></br>I also decided to plot my results for roll in 0.5 degree increments from 0 to 3 degrees. I believe this to be a realistic representation of the vehicle's actual roll as it is a fairly stiff set-up and would therefore not roll a huge amount.</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>The results I obtained and their graphical representations can be seen on the following pages.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="15">
         <content prompt="Type your Introduction here." eid="16" dup="7">
            <para prompt="Type your Introduction here." eid="16" dup="7"><![CDATA[]]>Introduction<![CDATA[
]]><p>This assignment deals with the analysis of one aspect of the suspension set-up of the formula student single-seater race car. The aim of the assignment is to determine how the suspension performance will change if the suspension geometry is altered. By modeling one area of the suspension … [describes the methodology and provides a rationale for the method], I chose to investigate the front suspension set-up of the car and, in particular, decided to investigate:</p><![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br>How changing the vertical position of the upper pickup points would affect camber compensation and the lateral position of the roll centre during roll.<![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>I chose to change position of the upper pickup points of the suspension by:<![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>+20 mm, +10 mm, -20 mm, -10 mm from the original position, as<useful type="objective" eid="17">I consider this to be</useful> a fairly<useful type="linking" eid="18">realistic</useful> range of changes that would be possible to make.<![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>I also decided to plot my results for roll in 0.5 degree increments from 0 to 3 degrees.<useful type="objective" eid="19">I believe this to be</useful> a<useful type="linking" eid="20">realistic</useful> representation of the vehicle's actual roll as it is a fairly stiff set-up and would therefore not roll a huge amount.<![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>The results I obtained and their graphical representations can be seen on the following pages.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="21">
         <name eid="22">Analysis and evaluation</name>
         <desc eid="23">An introductory evaluation is followed by a detailed presentation, discussion and evaluation of points.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type your Analysis and evaluation here." eid="24">
            <para prompt="Type your Analysis and evaluation here." eid="24"><![CDATA[]]>Analysis and evaluation of results<![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="25"><br></br>The results I obtained from the Mitchell analysis show some interesting results in the relationship between the vertical position of the upper pickup points and the performance indicators.</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="26"><br></br><br></br>Relationship with camber</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="27"><br></br>The results I obtained show that … [discussion of results] I do not have any data for the tyres used on the formula student, and cannot therefore make any definite decisions. With regard to camber compensation, I can, however, suggest that raising the position of the upper pickup points would be detrimental to the car's performance … This is definitely not what is required as it would reduce the contact patch between the road and tyre, therefore reducing grip. I would therefore suggest that the lower the position of the pickup, the better the camber compensation. This is not the definitive answer, however, as this may conflict with other performance indicators (discussed later).</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="28"><br></br><br></br>Relationship with lateral roll centre position</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="29"><br></br>The results I obtained show that … This would suggest that the higher the position of the pickup, the better the suspension will work. This is the complete opposite to the relationship between the pickup point and camber.</extra_info> <![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>Conflicts between results<![CDATA[
]]><extra_info eid="30"><br></br>The results I obtained for the performance indicators conflict completely with each other. … [More detail about the conflict is provided (omitted here).] This makes it very difficult to recommend any changes that could be made. This would be easier to achieve with some tyre data to work with.</extra_info> 
            </para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="31">
         <content prompt="Type your Analysis and evaluation here." eid="32" dup="24">
            <para prompt="Type your Analysis and evaluation here." eid="32" dup="24"><![CDATA[]]>Analysis and evaluation of results<![CDATA[
]]><br></br>The results I obtained from the Mitchell analysis show some<useful type="linking" eid="33">interesting</useful> results in the relationship between the vertical position of the upper pickup points and the performance indicators.<![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>Relationship with camber<![CDATA[
]]><br></br>The results I obtained show that … [discussion of results]<useful type="objective" eid="34">I do not have any data</useful> for the tyres used on the formula student,<useful type="objective" eid="35">and cannot therefore make any definite decisions</useful>. With regard to camber compensation,<useful type="structure" eid="36">I can, however, suggest</useful> that raising the position of the upper pickup points would be detrimental to the car's performance …<useful type="objective" eid="37">This is definitely not what is required</useful> as it would reduce the contact patch between the road and tyre, therefore reducing grip.<useful type="structure" eid="38">I would therefore suggest</useful> that the lower the position of the pickup, the better the camber compensation.<useful type="objective" eid="39">This is not the definitive answer</useful>, however, as this may conflict with other performance indicators (discussed later).<![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>Relationship with lateral roll centre position<![CDATA[
]]><br></br>The results I obtained show that …<useful type="structure" eid="40">This would suggest that</useful> the higher the position of the pickup, the better the suspension will work. This is the complete opposite to the relationship between the pickup point and camber.<![CDATA[
]]><?xm-replace_text {para}?><![CDATA[
]]><br></br><br></br>Conflicts between results<![CDATA[
]]><useful type="objective" eid="41"><br></br>The results I obtained for the performance indicators conflict completely with each other.</useful> … [More detail about the conflict is provided (omitted here).]<useful type="objective" eid="42">This makes it very</useful> 
               <useful type="linking" eid="43">difficult</useful> 
               <useful type="objective" eid="44">to recommend any changes</useful> that could be made.<useful type="structure" eid="45">This would be easier</useful> to achieve with some tyre data to work with.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="46">
         <name eid="47">Conclusion and recommendations</name>
         <desc eid="48">Summarize your evaluation and make any recommendations.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type your Conclusion and recommendations here." eid="49">
            <para prompt="Type your Conclusion and recommendations here." eid="49"><![CDATA[]]>Recommended modifications<![CDATA[
]]><br></br>I would recommend that ... I say this because … I believe that the<extra_info eid="50">improvements in camber compensation would outweigh the loss of grip caused by the movement of the RC. … I would suggest … I believe this to be the optimum position as it will improve the camber compensation without moving the RC out too far. Any more than this would, in my opinion, lead to too much loss in grip … This would mean that … Any further than this would provide excessive camber compensation and may lead to ... However, as I suggested earlier, this would depend entirely on the application, tyres and other unknown variables.</extra_info> 
               <extra_info eid="51">More data and further investigation would be required to give a more definitive answer to the best modifications.</extra_info> 
            </para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="52">
         <content prompt="Type your Conclusion and recommendations here."
                  eid="53"
                  dup="49">
            <para prompt="Type your Conclusion and recommendations here."
                  eid="53"
                  dup="49"><![CDATA[]]>Recommended modifications<![CDATA[
]]><br></br><useful type="structure" eid="54"><br></br>I would recommend</useful> that ... I say this because …<useful type="structure" eid="55">I believe that</useful> the improvements in camber compensation would outweigh the loss of grip caused by the movement of the RC. …<useful type="structure" eid="56">I would suggest</useful> …<useful type="structure" eid="57">I believe this to be</useful> the optimum position as it will improve the camber compensation without moving the RC out too far.<useful type="objective" eid="58">Any more than this would, in my opinion</useful>, lead to too much loss in grip …<useful type="structure" eid="59">This would mean that</useful> … Any further than this would provide excessive camber compensation and may lead to ... However,<useful type="structure" eid="60">as I suggested</useful> earlier, this would depend entirely on the application, tyres and other unknown variables.<useful type="structure" eid="61">More data and further investigation would be required</useful> to give a more<useful type="linking" eid="62">definitive</useful> answer to the best modifications.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
   </paragraphs>
</framework>
