<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<framework>
    <framework_title>Academic email</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure the email. There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your email.</para>
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="What is special about an academic email?">
            <commentary>
                <para>Academic emails are usually personal, not official. You are writing to a specific, named individual, not to somebody in their official role.</para>
				<para>Make sure that you use the appropriate level of formality. If you are writing to an academic for the first time, use formal language, particularly if they are outside your university or department.</para>
                <para>If you know the person you are writing to well, you can be less formal.</para>
                <para>If you need to make a request, you should take care to use polite language and avoid inconveniencing the reader or putting them under pressure.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is it structured?" para_ids="1,3,4,6,7,9,25,11,12,14,15,17,18,20,21">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to create this email.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How does the email start and finish?" para_ids="6,7,8,20,21,22">
            <commentary>
                <para>The email begins with 'Dear + academic title and family name, or Mr, Ms, etc. and family name'. It ends with a polite closing: 'Best wishes' (or 'Best regards'/'Regards').</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="10,13,16,19,22">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="23">The writer uses a polite and formal style.</para>
                <para showme="24">The writer acknowledges that the person they are writing to may be busy.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point>Use the framework to organize your own email.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_formal.swf">Use formal language if you do not know the person you are writing to.</point>
                <point help="email_politewrds.swf">Use polite words and phrases to make requests.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point>Use an appropriate greeting, ending and closing.</point>
                <point>Make sure that you use the appropriate level of formality. If you are writing to an academic for the first time, use formal language. If you know the person well, you can be less formal.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>If necessary, have I introduced myself in the first paragraph?</point>
                <point>Have I said why I am writing?</point>
                <point>Have I politely stated what I need?</point>
                <point>Does my email sound formal and polite?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar and spelling?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="1">Recipient's email address</name>
            <content eid="2" prompt="Type the email address you are writing to">
                <para>pbarr@email.co.uk</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="3">Subject</name>
            <desc eid="4">Use a clear, brief subject line.</desc>
            <content eid="5" prompt="Type the subject of your email">
                <para>Subject: Request for statistical help</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="6">Greeting</name>
			<desc eid="7">Dear…</desc>
            <tip>TIP Greeting: use 'Dear + academic title and family name, or Mr, Ms, etc. and family name'. You can use first names if you know the person you are writing to well.</tip>
            <content eid="8" prompt="Type 'Dear…'">
                <para>Dear Dr Barr</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="9">Paragraph 1</name>
            <desc eid="25">Introduce yourself by giving your position in the university.</desc>
            <content eid="10" prompt="Type your paragraph here">
                <para>I am a first year PhD student in the department of linguistics and my research topic is a quantitative study of verb forms in academic writing.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="11">Paragraph 2</name>
            <desc eid="12">Say why you are writing.</desc>
			<tip>TIP Give brief supporting/background information. Mention any academic contact.</tip>
            <content eid="13" prompt="Type your paragraph here">
                <para>As I need to use advanced statistical tools for processing the data, my supervisor, Dr John Pugh, suggested I contact you to ask for advice.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="14">Paragraph 3</name>
            <desc eid="15">State clearly what you need from them.</desc>
			<tip>TIP Remember the person you are writing to may be busy and acknowledge this. Only ask for something that is relatively easy for them to do and justify the need for your request.</tip>
            <content eid="16" prompt="Type your paragraph here">
                <para><extra_info eid="23">Would it be possible</extra_info> for me to come and see you to discuss what I need? Or <extra_info eid="24">if you are too busy to meet</extra_info>, <extra_info eid="23">perhaps we could</extra_info> talk on the phone? I attach a copy of my draft research proposal to give you an idea of the scope of my study.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="17">Ending</name>
            <desc eid="18">End very politely.</desc>
            <content eid="19" prompt="Type your ending here">
                <para><extra_info eid="23">I would be very grateful indeed for any help you could give me.</extra_info></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="20">Closing</name>
			<desc eid="21">Give your full name. Add position and contact details if necessary.</desc>
            <tip>TIP In a less formal email when you know the person you are writing to, 'Many thanks' can be used as a closing, and you can give just your first name.</tip>
            <content eid="22" prompt="Type 'Best wishes', 'Best regards', etc. and your name">
                <para>Best wishes</para>
                <para>David Brown</para>
                <para>024 7654 3210</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
