<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "Q:\rules\ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<!--Edited: 23 October 2009 09:45:16 by turnbulj-->
<framework>
    <framework_title>An argument or opinion essay. Framework 2</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure this type of essay. This framework presents an alternating series of arguments and counterarguments. There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your essay.</para>
        <para>Remember that you can look the word up in the Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_brainstorm.swf">Brainstorm your ideas on the question.</point>
                <point help="argument_read_and_research.swf">Read and research the topic.</point>
                <point>When researching, take detailed notes and keep an accurate record of each source.</point>
                <point>Which do you think are the strongest arguments? Decide what your viewpoint will be.</point>
                <point>Select 2 or 3 strong ideas on each side, with supporting examples, ideas or evidence. For some questions you can use evidence from your personal experience.</point>
                <point>Decide roughly how many words you will give to each part of your essay.</point>
                <point>Note down some useful vocabulary on the topic.</point>
                <point>Organize your notes into the framework.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_formal.swf">Use formal and impersonal language.</point>
                <point help="argument_phrases.swf">Use words and phrases to signal your  position.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_connecting_words.swf">Use connecting words and phrases to make the structure of your essay clear to your readers.</point>
                <point>Give  quotes or mention sources to support your points.</point>
                <point help="argument_make_clear.swf">Make it clear which words/ideas are yours and whose words/ideas you have quoted.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Have I answered the question?</point>
                <point>Have I introduced the subject, developed it logically and come to a conclusion?</point>
                <point>Have I given evidence, examples and reasons for each point I make?</point>
                <point>Does my conclusion follow from my arguments?</point>
                <point>Have I used paragraphs appropriately?</point>
                <point>Is it the right length?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar, spelling and punctuation?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Title</name>
            <desc>The title of your essay.</desc>
            <content prompt="Type your title here"/>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Introduction</name>
            <desc>Introduce the topic and state the focus of the essay.</desc>
            <tip>TIP Go from broad to narrow focus.</tip>
            <notes/>
            <content prompt="Type your introduction here"/>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Argument 1</name>
            <desc>Give the first argument with supporting evidence, examples or reasons.</desc>
            <tip>You can use one or more paragraphs for each argument.</tip>
            <notes/>
            <content/>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Counterargument</name>
            <desc>Give any arguments against point 1, with  evidence, examples or reasons.</desc>
            <tip>TIP You can use one or more paragraphs for each counterargument.</tip>
            <notes/>
            <content/>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Argument 2</name>
            <desc>Give the second argument with supporting evidence, examples or reasons.</desc>
            <notes/>
            <content/>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Counterargument</name>
            <desc>Give any arguments against point 2, with  evidence, examples or reasons.</desc>
            <notes/>
            <content/>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Further arguments and counterarguments.</name>
            <desc>Alternate further arguments and counterarguments.</desc>
            <tip>TIP Start a new paragraph for each argument and counterargument.</tip>
            <notes/>
            <content/>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Evaluation of arguments</name>
            <desc>Explain which you feel are the stronger arguments, with reasons.</desc>
            <notes/>
            <content/>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name>Summary and conclusion</name>
            <desc>Summarize the points you have made and state the conclusion you have come to on the question or title of the essay.</desc>
            <tip>TIP The conclusion may go from narrow to broad focus.</tip>
            <notes/>
            <content prompt="Type your conclusion here"/>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
