<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<framework>
    <framework_title>Article</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure this article. There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your article.</para>
        <para>You can visit the help section to learn more about Oxford iWriter.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="What is special about writing an article?">
            <commentary>
                <para>In some exams you are asked to write an article for a fictional magazine or website. You are required to use your imagination and write in a particular style that engages the reader. It could mean writing about a hobby or something you are passionate about, making recommendations about something related to culture or lifestyle, or giving your opinion on a current issue. The language is usually informal and more similar to spoken English rather than formal academic English.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is it structured?" para_ids="3,4,6,7,10,11,14,15">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to create this article.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How was it planned?" para_ids="1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8,10,11,12,14,15,16">
            <commentary>
                <para>In order to plan the article, the writer decides what to cover in each paragraph and takes notes.</para>
				<para>Around four paragraphs is best for a short article.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Focus on the introduction" para_ids="5,6,7,9">
            <commentary>
                <para>The purpose of an introduction is to introduce the main idea. Keep it short and simple.</para>
				<para showme="i1,i2">The writer asks rhetorical questions (= questions asked for effect, not expecting an answer) to help the reader engage directly with the article.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Look at the main section" para_ids="5,10,11,13">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="i3,i4">The writer uses short sentences for dramatic effect. You can include just one or two that don't even have a verb.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Catching the reader's attention" para_ids="5,9,13,17">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="i5">Think of an imaginative title using an unusual or surprising word.</para>
				<para showme="i6,i7,i8,i9,i10">Use imperatives and 'you' and 'your' to address the reader directly.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Focus on the conclusion" para_ids="5,14,15,17">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="i11,i12">Use the conclusion to link back to the original idea in the introduction.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_brainstorm.swf">Brainstorm some ideas, keep the best four and delete the rest.</point>
                <point>Provide examples from real life.</point>
                <point>Think about how to keep up the reader's interest from the beginning through to the end.</point>
				<point>Organize your notes into the framework.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point>Use relatively informal language. Avoid any formal or academic language.</point>
                <point help="dramaticlanguages.swf">Use dramatic language to make your article engaging.</point>
                <point>Address your target audience directly and use terms and phrases that make your reader feel you understand them.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point help="rhetoricalquestions.swf">Ask rhetorical questions to help the reader engage directly with the article.</point>
                <point help="ideaphrases.swf">Use phrases to organize your ideas.</point>
				<point>Use short sentences that all add value to the article.</point>
				<point help="expressopinion.swf">Don't be afraid to express your opinion and give the reader something to think about.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Have I answered the question?</point>
                <point>Have I chosen an imaginative title?</point>
                <point>Does the introduction introduce the main idea?</point>
                <point>Do the next paragraphs build on the main idea and give examples?</point>
                <point>Does my conclusion link back to the original idea?</point>
				<point>Is it the right length?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar, spelling and punctuation?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="1">Question</name>
            <content eid="2" prompt="Type your question here">
                <para><strong>Articles wanted for our new lifestyle magazine. Write your article in 140-190 words using the appropriate style.</strong></para>
				<para><strong><i>What smart or interesting ways can you think of that would help people improve their lifestyles? How can they be more organized? How can they improve their diet? How can they be more productive?</i></strong></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="3">Title</name>
            <desc eid="4">The title of your article</desc>
            <content eid="5" prompt="Type your title here">
                <para><extra_info eid="i5"><strong>Lifehacks</strong></extra_info></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="6">Introduction</name>
            <desc eid="7">Introduce the main idea.</desc>
            <notes eid="8">
                <para>Definition of 'hacks' and summary of how they can help</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="9" prompt="Type your introduction here">
                <para><extra_info eid="i1">Have you ever felt</extra_info> you could improve your lifestyle? Imagine you are an Olympic athlete analysing your training and performance, looking for ways to improve everything by a small amount—better shoes, more effective training, stronger muscles. The end result is a combination of lots of mini improvements or ‘hacks’ that help you stay ahead. <extra_info eid="i2">Would you like</extra_info> to be a champion? Here’s how.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="10">Main section</name>
            <desc eid="11">Build on the main idea and provide examples.</desc>
            <notes eid="12">
                <para>Get up early and plan your day.</para>
                <para>Take five minutes off during the day without any distractions.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="13" prompt="Type your main section here">
                <para><extra_info eid="i3">First things first.</extra_info> Don’t get up at the last minute and rush out of the house. Get up ten minutes earlier. Use the time to plan and decide on your main aim for the day. Feel relaxed and prepared when you open the front door.</para>
                <para>During the day, <extra_info eid="i6">take five minutes off</extra_info>. <extra_info eid="i4">No distractions.</extra_info> <extra_info eid="i7">Turn off your smartphone</extra_info>. <extra_info eid="i8">Don’t talk to anyone</extra_info> and don’t look at any texts or messages. Just let your mind relax. When you get back to your desk you’ll be ready for the next big challenge.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="14">Conclusions</name>
            <desc eid="15">Link back to the original idea in the introduction.</desc>
            <notes eid="16">
                <para>Do new things—cook, read, learn how to do something.</para>
				<para>Make the most of your day.</para>
				<para>Go to bed tired and happy.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="17" prompt="Type your conclusions here">
                <para>When you get home don’t just heat up a pizza and watch TV—cook something you’ve never cooked before. Read something rather than watch TV. Watch a YouTube video and <extra_info eid="i9">learn a language</extra_info> or <extra_info eid="i10">find out how to fix your bike</extra_info>. Go to bed tired and happy knowing <extra_info eid="i11">you’ve</extra_info> made the most of your day and <extra_info eid="i12">improved your lifestyle</extra_info>—just a little bit.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
