<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<!--Edited: 02 November 2009 17:15:37 by turnbulj-->
<framework>
    <framework_title>A comparison and contrast essay 1 (Emphasizing the differences)</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure this type of essay. This framework emphasizes the differences by presenting all the similarities first, followed by all the differences. There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your essay.</para>
        <para>Remember that you can look the word up in the Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="How do I organize a comparison essay?">
            <commentary>
                <para>There are several different ways you can organize your ideas and arguments in an essay that is comparing and contrasting two things, ideas, institutions, etc.</para>
                <para>In this model the writer wants to emphasize the differences between the types of  schools. The similarities are discussed in one paragraph first, followed by a paragraph each for the two most important differences and a third paragraph for more minor differences.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is this essay structured?" para_ids="2,3,6,7,16,17,25,26,39,40">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to create this essay.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How was it planned?" para_ids="2,3,6,7,16,17,25,26,39,40,4,8,18,27,41">
            <commentary>
                <para>In order to plan the essay, the writer decides what to cover in each paragraph and takes notes.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Focus on the introduction" para_ids="4,6,7,12">
            <commentary>
                <para>The purpose of an introduction is to explain the subject of your essay (the situation or problem, etc.), and how you intend to deal with it. A typical introduction moves from a general statement to a more specific focus.</para>
                <para showme="13">Sentences 1 and 2 catch the reader's interest.</para>
                <para showme="14">Sentence 4 indicates the scope of the essay and leads to the next paragraph.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Look at the main paragraphs" para_ids="4,16,17,19,25,26,28">
            <commentary>
                <para>The writer notes 2 similarities in paragraph 2.</para>
                <para>The writer concentrates on differences in the rest of the paragraphs.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Focus on the conclusion" para_ids="4,39,40,46">
            <commentary>
                <para>The purpose of a conclusion is to clearly and confidently express your point of view on the question at hand.</para>
                <para showme="47">The first sentence summarizes the findings of the essay.</para>
                <para showme="48">The second sentence gives the writer's personal opinion.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="4,9,19,28,42">
            <commentary>
                <para>The writer uses key words or phrases to:</para>
                <para showme="20,21,22,23">introduce similarities</para>
                <para showme="10,11,29,30,31,32,33,34,35,36,37,43,44,45">introduce contrasts</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_brainstorm.swf">Brainstorm ideas about similarities and differences. For example, arrange points in a table.</point>
                <point help="argument_read_and_research.swf">Read and research the topic.</point>
                <point>Highlight the similarities and the differences and decide which are more important.</point>
                <point>Choose which points to include in your essay and which to leave out.</point>
                <point>Decide how to define the two things you are comparing.</point>
                <point>Organize your notes into the framework.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_formal.swf">Use formal and impersonal language.</point>
                <point help="compare_words_differences.swf">Use words and phrases to describe differences.</point>
                <point help="compare_words_similarities.swf">Use words and phrases to describe similarities.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_connecting_words.swf">Use connecting words and phrases to make the structure of your essay clear to your readers.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Have I answered the question?</point>
                <point>Have I introduced the subject, developed it logically and come to a conclusion?</point>
                <point>Does the conclusion follow logically from the rest of the essay?</point>
                <point>Have I used paragraphs appropriately?</point>
                <point>Is it the right length?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar, spelling and punctuation?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph eid="1">
            <name eid="2">Title</name>
            <desc eid="3">The title of your essay.</desc>
            <content eid="4" prompt="Type your title here">
                <para><strong>Are private schools better than state schools?</strong></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="5">
            <name eid="6">Introduction</name>
            <desc eid="7">Introduce the topic and explain the scope of the essay.</desc>
            <notes eid="8">
                <para>Parents - have choice of state or private schools.</para>
                <para>Definition: state schools = no fees; private schools = fees.</para>
                <para>Important to look at differences - esp. curriculum, quality of teaching, achievement.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="9" prompt="Type your introduction here">
                <para>For parents, few things are more important than their child's education. In many countries, parents of school-age children can choose to send their child to a private school rather than to a state school. In this essay, state schools are defined as those that do not charge tuition fees because they are funded and run by local or central government; private schools, <useful type="contrast" eid="10">on the other hand</useful>, are funded almost entirely by the fees that they charge. Before deciding where to educate their child, parents need to examine the <useful type="contrast" eid="11">differences between</useful> the two types of school, particularly as regards the curriculum, the quality of tuition and student achievement.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <content eid="12" dup="9">
                <para>
                    <extra_info eid="13">For parents, few things are more important than their child's education. In many countries, parents of school-age children can choose to send their child to a private school rather than to a state school.</extra_info> In this essay, state schools are defined as those that do not charge tuition fees because they are funded and run by local or central government; private schools, on the other hand, are funded almost entirely by the fees that they charge. <extra_info eid="14">Before deciding where to educate their child, parents need to examine the differences between the two types of school, particularly as regards the curriculum, the quality of tuition and student achievement.</extra_info>
                </para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="15">
            <name eid="16">Similarities</name>
            <desc eid="17">Explain the aspects or features of X and Y that are similar.</desc>
            <tip>TIP You can use several paragraphs here.</tip>
            <notes eid="18">
                <para>Both have same aim: to increase knowledge, prepare for future.</para>
                <para>Both have same organization: - terms/semesters and assessments.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="19">
                <para>Private and state schools <useful type="similarity" eid="20">are comparable</useful> in some respects. <useful type="similarity" eid="21">Like</useful> state schools, private schools aim to develop the knowledge, skills and character of students, in order to prepare them for their future lives. <useful type="similarity" eid="22">Both</useful> types of school <useful type="similarity" eid="23">are also very similar</useful> in the way they organize their teaching and assessment, using terms or semesters with assessments at the end of the academic year.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="24">
            <name eid="25">Differences</name>
            <desc eid="26">Move on to explain the aspects or features of X and Y that are different.</desc>
            <tip>TIP You can use several paragraphs here.</tip>
            <notes eid="27">
                <para>Main differences: range of subjects -  more in private schools. State schools have national curriculum.</para>
                <para>: teachers - higher pay in private schools = more specialized teachers?</para>
                <para>: class sizes - smaller in private schools = better discipline and higher standards.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="28">
                <para>
                    <useful type="contrast" eid="29">Despite these similarities</useful>, there are a number of <useful type="contrast" eid="30">marked differences</useful> in the way that state and private schools operate. The range of subjects taught at state schools is largely limited by the demands of the national curriculum. <useful type="contrast" eid="31">In contrast</useful>, private schools can offer a greater choice of subjects, because they generally have <useful type="contrast" eid="32">more</useful> money to spend on equipment, technology and staff <useful type="contrast" eid="33">than</useful> state schools do.</para>
                <para>Teachers working within the state system must have recognized teaching qualifications and are paid according to a national scale. Private schools, however, are in a position to offer <useful type="contrast" eid="34">higher</useful> salaries and may therefore be able to attract subject specialists who have considerable expertise in their field.</para>
                <para>In general, it is true to say that <useful type="contrast" eid="35">while</useful> state schools have a high student-teacher ratio, private schools tend to offer <useful type="contrast" eid="36">smaller</useful> classes. This may lead to <useful type="contrast" eid="37">better</useful> discipline in private schools with the result that students may achieve somewhat higher academic standards.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="38">
            <name eid="39">Conclusion</name>
            <desc eid="40">Draw your own conclusion based on the evidence from the development section of the essay.</desc>
            <notes eid="41">
                <para>Differences are important - private schools may have advantages. Balance this against fees.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="42" prompt="Type your conclusion here">
                <para>It is clear, therefore, that there are <useful type="contrast" eid="43">significant differences between</useful> private and state schools and that private schools may offer advantages. The benefits of private schooling must, <useful type="contrast" eid="44">however</useful>, be <useful type="contrast" eid="45">balanced against</useful> the cost involved and each family's budget priorities.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <content eid="46" dup="42">
                <para>
                    <extra_info eid="47">It is clear, therefore, that there are significant differences between private and state schools and that private schools may offer advantages.</extra_info>
                    <extra_info eid="48">The benefits of private schooling must, however, be balanced against the cost involved and each family's budget priorities.</extra_info>
                </para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
