<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<framework>
    <framework_title>A comparison and contrast essay 1-a (Emphasizing the differences)</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure this type of essay. This framework emphasizes the differences by presenting all the similarities first, followed by all the differences. There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your essay.</para>
        <para>Remember that you can look the word up in the Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="How do I organize a comparison essay?">
            <commentary>
                <para>There are several different ways you can organize your ideas and arguments in an essay that is comparing and contrasting two things, ideas, institutions, etc.</para>
                <para>In this model the writer wants to emphasize the differences between the types of  schools. The similarities are discussed in one paragraph first, followed by a paragraph each for the two most important differences and a third paragraph for more minor differences.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is this essay structured?" para_ids="2,3,6,7,16,17,25,26,33,34">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to create this essay.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How was it planned?" para_ids="2,3,6,7,16,17,25,26,33,34,4,8,18,27,35">
            <commentary>
                <para>In order to plan the essay, the writer decides what to cover in each paragraph and takes notes.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Focus on the introduction" para_ids="4,6,7,9">
            <commentary>
                <para>The introduction gives a short summary of the current situation.</para>
                <para showme="13">The second sentence catches the reader's interest.</para>
                <para showme="14">Sentence 4 indicates the scope of the essay and leads to the next paragraph.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Look at the development section" para_ids="4,16,17,19,25,26,28">
            <commentary>
                <para>The writer notes similarities between X and Y in paragraph 2.</para>
                <para>The writer concentrates on differences and discusses the advantages of X and Y in paragraphs 3-6.</para>
				<para showme="29">'Despite these similarities' indicates that the writer is going to list the differences.</para>
				<para showme="30">'However' indicates that the writer is now going to change focus and discuss the advantages of traditional courses.</para>
				<para showme="31">The writer provides data to support the argument that traditional courses are more effective to provide balance to the overall argument.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Focus on the conclusion" para_ids="33,34,36">
            <commentary>
                <para>The writer provides a conclusion based on the main points introduced in the development stages.</para>
                <para showme="37">The paragraph starts with a short summary.</para>
                <para showme="38">The final sentence gives the writer's personal opinion.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="4,12,19,44,39">
            <commentary>
                <para>The writer uses key words or phrases to:</para>
                <para showme="40,41,42,43">introduce similarities</para>
                <para showme="45,46,47,48,49,50,51,52,53,54">introduce contrasts</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point>If possible, choose a question related to the topic you are most familiar with.</point>
				<point>Read the question carefully several times. Underline the key task words and topic words.</point>
                <point help="argument_read_and_research.swf">Read and research the topic.</point>
				<point help="argument_brainstorm.swf">Brainstorm ideas about similarities and differences. For example, arrange points in a table.</point>
                <point>Organize your ideas. Cut any ideas that don’t help you answer the question.</point>
                <point>Define the two things you are comparing so that the reader is clear what you are referring to.</point>
                <point>Highlight the similarities and the differences and decide on your conclusion.</point>
				<point>Organize your notes into the framework.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_formal.swf">Use formal and impersonal language.</point>
                <point help="compare_words_differences-a.swf">Use words and phrases to describe differences.</point>
                <point help="compare_words_similarities-a.swf">Use words and phrases to describe similarities.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
				<point>Think of a fact or comment that captures the reader’s interest in the introduction.</point>
                <point help="argument_connecting_words.swf">Use connecting words and phrases to make the structure of your essay clear to your readers.</point>
				<point>Identify opportunities to develop your ideas and show your range of language.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Have I answered the question?</point>
                <point>Have I introduced the subject, developed it logically and come to a conclusion?</point>
                <point>Does the conclusion follow logically from the rest of the essay?</point>
                <point>Have I used paragraphs appropriately?</point>
                <point>Is it the right length?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar, spelling and punctuation?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph eid="1">
            <name eid="2">Title</name>
            <desc eid="3">The title of your essay</desc>
            <content eid="4" prompt="Type your title here">
                <para><strong>Which is more effective, online or traditional classroom learning?</strong></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="5">
            <name eid="6">Introduction</name>
            <desc eid="7">Introduce the topic and define the things you are comparing.</desc>
            <notes eid="8">
                <para>Changes due to technology—large increase in online courses</para>
                <para>380 000 learners for one English MOOC</para>
                <para>Traditional courses still available.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="9" prompt="Type your introduction here">
                <para>
				Technology has brought about significant changes in education and the number of students taking courses online has increased dramatically. <extra_info eid="13">Recently 380 000 learners signed up for one online English course, the most ever for a MOOC (massive open online course).</extra_info> At the same time, traditional universities continue to provide face-to-face tutorials, seminars and lectures for relatively small numbers of students. <extra_info eid="14">Which of these forms of learning is more effective and how do we know?</extra_info>
				</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <content eid="12" dup="9">
                <para>
				Technology has brought about significant changes in education and the number of students taking courses online has increased dramatically. Recently 380 000 learners signed up for one online English course, the most ever for a MOOC (massive open online course). At the same time, traditional universities continue to provide face-to-face tutorials, seminars and lectures for relatively small numbers of students. Which of these forms of learning is more effective and how do we know?
                </para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="15">
            <name eid="16">Development—similarities</name>
            <desc eid="17">Explain the aspects or features of X and Y that are similar.</desc>
            <tip>TIP You can use several paragraphs here.</tip>
            <notes eid="18">
                <para>Both have same aim: to provide structured education</para>
                <para>Both cover same content: syllabus, course notes</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="19">
                <para>
					<useful type="similarity" eid="40">Both</useful> online courses and face-to-face courses have the same aims—to provide a structured educational experience for students that allows them to learn a given subject effectively. Online courses <useful type="similarity" eid="41">are similar to</useful> traditional courses in that they have a syllabus and <useful type="similarity" eid="42">also</useful> provide learning materials such as course notes.
				</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="24">
            <name eid="25">Development—differences</name>
            <desc eid="26">Move on to explain the aspects or features of X and Y that are different.</desc>
            <tip>TIP You can use several paragraphs here.</tip>
            <notes eid="27">
                <para>Main differences:</para>
                <para>—Online: continuous access, learn anywhere; traditional: fixed time and place</para>
                <para>—Online: unlimited students, digital materials, cheaper or free; traditional: buildings, teachers, limited number of students</para>
				<para>—Face-to-face contact: immediate answers to questions; social interaction good for motivation.</para>
				<para>—Completion rates for courses online: sometimes only 13%; traditional: 70-80%</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="28">
                <para>
                    <extra_info eid="29">Despite these similarities,</extra_info> there are a number of significant differences between the two types of course. The main advantage of online courses is that students have continuous access to the learning material, and learning can be done anywhere at any time. On the other hand, face-to-face learning happens only in the classroom according to a fixed timetable. This is a disadvantage for students who also have to work and for students who live far away from the college or school.
				</para>
                <para>
					Unlike traditional courses, which require buildings and teachers, online courses only need a website and digital learning materials. Added to this, online courses can take an almost unlimited number of students, while traditional courses are limited to the number of people that can fit into a lecture hall. The end result is that online courses are much cheaper, and in some cases, free.
				</para>
                <para>
					<extra_info eid="30">However,</extra_info> the news is not all good for online courses. It seems that students prefer face-to-face contact with their lecturers and classmates. Students can get immediate answers to questions in a lecture or tutorial rather than wait for an email or chatroom message. Social interaction with their peers not only helps their motivation but also develops their social skills.
				</para>
                <para>
					It appears that the personal or affective element of traditional courses is crucial. <extra_info eid="31">Some online courses have completion rates as low as 13%, whereas between 70–80% of students on traditional courses complete their degrees.</extra_info> Despite their low cost and convenience, online courses cannot yet compete with the timeless advantage of students being able to communicate face-to-face and to be part of a real, rather than virtual, community.
				</para>
            </content>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
            <content eid="44" dup="28">
                <para>
                    <useful type="contrast" eid="45">Despite these similarities,</useful> there are a number of significant <useful type="contrast" eid="46">differences</useful> between the two types of course. The main advantage of online courses is that students have continuous access to the learning material, and learning can be done anywhere at any time. <useful type="contrast" eid="47">On the other hand,</useful> face-to-face learning happens only in the classroom according to a fixed timetable. This is a disadvantage for students who also have to work and for students who live far away from the college or school.
				</para>
                <para>
					<useful type="contrast" eid="48">Unlike</useful> traditional courses, which require buildings and teachers, online courses only need a website and digital learning materials. Added to this, online courses can take an almost unlimited number of students, <useful type="contrast" eid="49">while</useful> traditional courses are limited to the number of people that can fit into a lecture hall. The end result is that online courses are <useful type="contrast" eid="50">much cheaper,</useful> and in some cases, free.
				</para>
                <para>
					<useful type="contrast" eid="51">However,</useful> the news is not all good for online courses. It seems that students <useful type="contrast" eid="52">prefer</useful> face-to-face contact with their lecturers and classmates. Students can get immediate answers to questions in a lecture or tutorial <useful type="contrast" eid="53">rather than</useful> wait for an email or chatroom message. Social interaction with their peers not only helps their motivation but also develops their social skills.
				</para>
                <para>
					It appears that the personal or affective element of traditional courses is crucial. Some online courses have completion rates as low as 13%, <useful type="contrast" eid="54">whereas</useful> between 70–80% of students on traditional courses complete their degrees. Despite their low cost and convenience, online courses cannot yet compete with the timeless advantage of students being able to communicate face-to-face and to be part of a real, rather than virtual, community.
				</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="32">
            <name eid="33">Conclusion</name>
            <desc eid="34">Draw your own conclusion based on the evidence from the development section of the essay.</desc>
            <notes eid="35">
                <para>Both types aim to provide education. Effectiveness depends on circumstances of providers and students.</para>
				<para>If available, traditional seems most effective.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="36" prompt="Type your conclusion here">
                <para>
					<extra_info eid="37">There are clearly significant differences between the two types of course, despite the fact that they share the same primary aim of providing an educational service.</extra_info> Ultimately, the answer as to which is more effective lies in the priorities of the provider and the students. For some providers, the target is to maximize the number of students who can take their courses; for others, the aim is to provide a high-quality, personalized education. <extra_info eid="38">For students who are not able to attend courses in person for financial or geographical reasons, online courses can be an effective solution; but for students who are lucky enough to have the opportunity, traditional courses, at least for now, seem to be the most effective and popular option.</extra_info>
				</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <content eid="39" dup="36">
                <para>
                    There are clearly significant differences between the two types of course, despite the fact that they <useful type="similarity" eid="43">share</useful> the same primary aim of providing an educational service. Ultimately, the answer as to which is more effective lies in the priorities of the provider and the students. For some providers, the target is to maximize the number of students who can take their courses; for others, the aim is to provide a high-quality, personalized education. For students who are not able to attend courses in person for financial or geographical reasons, online courses can be an effective solution; but for students who are lucky enough to have the opportunity, traditional courses, at least for now, seem to be the most effective and popular option.
                </para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
