<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "Q:\rules\ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<!--Edited: 20 October 2009 16:15:39 by turnbulj-->
<!--Edited: 20 October 2009 16:14:57 by turnbulj-->
<framework>
    <framework_title>A covering/cover letter </framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure this type of letter. There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your letter.</para>
        <para>Remember that you can look the word up in the Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="What is a covering/cover letter?">
            <commentary>
                <para>A covering letter (&#60;i&#62;NAmE&#60;/i&#62; cover letter) accompanies a CV/résumé or an application form. It can be a letter, an email, or part of an online form, but the content and language will be essentially the same. In Britain and North America they are usually typed on a single page. A good letter uses formal language and presents some key arguments for why you are a strong candidate. This is achieved by relating your skills and experience to the requirements of the job being applied for.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is it structured?" para_ids="2,6,9,13,18,19,23,26,27,34,35,45,46,55,56,62,63">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to create this letter.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is it laid out?" para_ids="2,4,6,7,9,11,13,16">
            <commentary>
                <para>Write your address, but not your name, in the top right-hand corner.</para>
                <para>The date can go either on the left or the right under the address, or above the address on the left.  It could also be January 20, 2010, (&#60;i&#62;BrE&#60;/i&#62;) 20/1/10, or (&#60;i&#62;NAmE&#60;/i&#62;) 1/20/10.</para>
                <para>Write the name, position and address of the person you are writing to on the left-hand side.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How does the letter start and finish?" para_ids="18,19,21,62,63,65">
            <commentary>
                <para>The writer knows the name of the person he is writing to, so begins 'Dear Mrs Hunter', and ends 'Yours sincerely'.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="30,38,49,58">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="31,32,39,40,41,42,43,50,51,52,53,59,60">The writer uses key words or phrases for a covering/cover letter.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point>Use the framework to organize notes for your own letter.</point>
                <point>Make sure your letter is appropriate for the job you are applying for.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point help="argument_formal.swf">Use formal language.</point>
                <point help="cover_letter_appropriate.swf">Use appropriate words and phrases.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point help="covering_letter_lay_your.swf">Lay your letter out correctly.</point>
                <point>Say what you can bring to the job.</point>
				<point>Make sure your letter is appropriate for the job you are applying for.</point>
                <point help="coverl_greeting_and_close.swf">Make sure the greeting and close match.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Have I given a reference?</point>
                <point>Does my first paragraph make it clear why I am writing?</point>
                <point>Have I said what I can bring to the job?</point>
                <point>Do the greeting and the close match?</point>
                <point>Does my letter sound quite formal?</point>
                <point>Is it polite?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar and spelling?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph eid="1" align="right">
            <name eid="2">Your address</name>
            <tip eid="3">TIP Write your address, but not your name, in the top right-hand corner.</tip>
            <content eid="4" prompt="Type your address here" align="right">
                <para>19 Strangelands Road</para>
                <para>London</para>
                <para>NE23 6ZB</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="5" align="right">
            <name eid="6">Your telephone number</name>
            <content eid="7" prompt="Type your telephone number here" align="right">
                <para>Tel: 0207 337 34589</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="8" align="right">
            <name eid="9">Date</name>
            <tip eid="10">TIP This can go either on the left or the right under the address, or above the address on the left.  It could also be January 20, 2010, 20/1/10 (&#60;i&#62;BrE&#60;/i&#62;), or (&#60;i&#62;NAmE&#60;/i&#62;) 1/20/10.</tip>
            <content eid="11" prompt="Type today's date here" align="right">
                <para>20 January 2010</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="12">
            <name eid="13">Employer's name and address</name>
            <tip eid="15">TIP Write the name, position and address of the person you are writing to on the left-hand side. If you are writing in American style use American spelling and punctuation e.g. write Mrs., Dr., etc.</tip>
            <content eid="16" prompt="Type the employer's name and address here">
                <para>Mrs F. Hunter</para>
                <para>Human Resources Manager</para>
                <para>Timson Office Supplies</para>
                <para>Unit 5 Males Industrial Estate</para>
                <para>Cambridge</para>
                <para>CB7 9HD</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="17">
            <name eid="18">Greeting</name>
            <desc eid="19">Dear...</desc>
            <tip eid="20">TIP Use 'Dear Sir or Madam' if you do not know the name of the person you are writing to. If you do know the name, use the form 'Dear Ms Klein', 'Dear Mr Smith'. If you do not know the gender you can use 'Dear Chris White', but do not use both title and first name. If you are writing in American style and you do not know the name of the person you are writing to, you can use 'To whom it may concern'.</tip>
            <content eid="21" prompt="Type Dear...">
                <para>Dear Mrs Hunter</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="22">
            <name eid="23">Reference: name of post</name>
            <content eid="24" prompt="Type a reference here">
                <para>Senior Accounts Clerk</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="25">
            <name eid="26">Paragraph 1</name>
            <desc eid="27">State your purpose for writing. Say which job you are applying for and how/where you heard about it.</desc>
            <tip eid="28">TIP In a covering letter use the words 'post', 'position' or 'vacancy', not 'job'. Avoid contracted forms such as I'm.</tip>
            <notes eid="29"/>
            <content eid="30">
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="31">I am writing to apply for the post of</useful> senior accounts clerk <useful type="key" eid="32">advertised in</useful> last Friday's edition of the <i>Cambridge Evening News</i> of 17 January.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="33">
            <name eid="34">Paragraph 2</name>
            <desc eid="35">This outlines your current job and responsibilities, or your qualifications if you are a new graduate.</desc>
            <tip eid="36">TIP Make this information relevant to the post you are applying for.</tip>
            <notes eid="37"/>
            <content eid="38">
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="39">As you will see from</useful> my enclosed CV, <useful type="key" eid="40">I am currently</useful> an accounts clerk in a medium-sized printing firm. <useful type="key" eid="41">In addition to</useful> my normal bookkeeping duties, <useful type="key" eid="42">I am responsible for</useful> invoicing and chasing up late payments. <useful type="key" eid="43">I also deal with</useful> credit checks on potential customers.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="44">
            <name eid="45">Paragraph 3</name>
            <desc eid="46">Say why you want the job and what you can bring to the company.</desc>
            <tip eid="47">TIP It is very important to say what you can do for them.</tip>
            <notes eid="48"/>
            <content eid="49">
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="50">I am committed to pursuing a career in</useful> management accounting and am currently studying for further professional qualifications by distance learning. <useful type="key" eid="51">I am particularly interested in</useful> your post as it would enable me to <useful type="key" eid="52">gain experience of</useful> working in a larger company with the opportunities for professional training and development that this brings. In addition to my skills and experience as an accounts clerk, <useful type="key" eid="53">I would bring to the job a proven ability to</useful> deal successfully and tactfully with customers and clients.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="54">
            <name eid="55">Paragraph 4</name>
            <desc eid="56">Give any other relevant information and say when you are available for interview.</desc>
            <notes eid="57"/>
            <content eid="58">
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="59">I am available for interview</useful> for the next three weeks, but will be away for two weeks from 14 February. <useful type="key" eid="60">I can supply details of</useful>  referees and any other information you may require.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="61">
            <name eid="62">Closing</name>
            <desc eid="63">Sign your name and print it in full underneath. Enc. or encl. shows you have enclosed something.
            </desc>
            <tip eid="64">TIP If you begin 'Dear + a name', end 'Yours sincerely'. Use 'Yours faithfully' here if you have begun 'Dear Sir or Madam'.
                In American style end your letter 'Sincerely', 'Sincerely yours', (if you use Dear + a name) or 'Yours truly'.</tip>
            <content prompt="Type 'Yours sincerely', 'Yours faithfully' etc, and your name" eid="65">
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="66">I look forward to hearing from you.</useful>
                </para>
                <para>Yours sincerely</para>
                <para>Dilip Patel</para>
                <para>Enc. CV</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
