<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<!--Edited: 02 September 2009 10:23:01 by turnbulj-->
<!--Edited: 13 May 2009 14:42:09 by bradyf-->
<!--Edited: 05 May 2009 16:28:19 by bradyf-->
<!--
Edited: 05 May 2009 15:50:17 by bradyf-->
<framework>
    <framework_title> British-style CV: new graduate</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure your CV if you are applying for your first job. There are spaces for you to add the content of your CV.</para>
        <para>You can visit the help section to learn more about Oxford iWriter.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="What is a CV for?">
            <commentary>
                <para>CVs and résumés are essential documents for the initial stage of applying for a job. They are both accounts of someone’s education, qualifications, skills and work experience.</para>
				<para>In the US, a résumé is a short summary of a person’s experience and qualifications, while a CV is more often used for academic positions and is a longer, more comprehensive document. In the UK, a CV is similar to an American résumé and is a summary of an applicant’s education and work experience that is adapted to the job being applied for. For all types of CV and résumé, the information given must be up to date and accurate.</para>
                <para>It is advisable to check with a teacher or tutor if there are any special conventions you should use. </para>
                <para>Also look at the covering/cover letter.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is it structured?" para_ids="1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 13, 15">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to create this CV.</para>
				<para>A CV should include all the relevant experience, skills and qualifications for the job being applied for as well as details of your education starting from your final year at school. You can draw out further relevant experience and highlight your skills in the covering letter that accompanies the CV.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Personal information" para_ids="1, 2">
            <commentary>
                <para>The labels, 'Name', Address', etc. can be omitted. There is no need to mention your age, gender, nationality, race, religion or marital status. Don't send a photo unless you are asked to.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Objective/Profile " para_ids="3, 4, 5, 6">
            <commentary>
                <para>These sections give an employer an idea of what you are looking for and who you are. Some people do not include these sections.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Education and qualifications" para_ids="7,8">
            <commentary>
                <para>Put the most recent first and do not include information about primary school. Add prizes and awards. Try to give British equivalents of your qualifications.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Work experience" para_ids="9, 10">
            <commentary>
                <para>This is also shown in reverse order, beginning with the most recent. As this is the CV of a recent graduate it includes holiday and part-time work. </para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Skills" para_ids="11, 12">
            <commentary>
                <para>These are the practical abilities of the applicant. The section also includes any formal qualifications relating to these skills.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Interests" para_ids="13, 14">
            <commentary>
                <para>This is a short section. It includes things like sport, creative activities and community activities, but not vague subjects such as 'reading' or 'travel'.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="References" para_ids="15, 16">
            <commentary>
                <para>These are the names and addresses of people who know you and who can give information to a potential employer about your character and abilities.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point>Collect together all the information you need to include in your CV</point>
                <point>Select information that is relevant to the job you are applying for</point>
                <point>Make sure all the information is accurate</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point help="cv_use_action_verbs.swf">Use action verbs and adjectives to present yourself positively.</point>
                <point help="cv_use_appropriate.swf">Use appropriate vocabulary to describe your skills and experience.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point>Organize the information into the framework.</point>
                <point>Show Education and Work experience in reverse order, beginning with the most recent.</point>
                <point>Use either full sentences (e.g. I taught French at a summer school) or note form (Taught French at summer school).</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Have I kept my CV short? (no more than 2 pages if possible)</point>
                <point>Have I used capitals, bold type, spacing and underlining to make my CV attractive and easy to read?</point>
                <point>Have I used a typeface such as Times New Roman, Arial or Verdana in at least 10 pt?</point>
                <point>Have I used reasonable margins on the page?</point>
                <point>Have I checked spelling and punctuation?</point>
				<point>Have I asked someone to read and edit the CV for me?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="1">Personal information</name>
            <tip>TIP You can omit the labels. There is no need to mention your age, gender, nationality, race, religion or marital status. Don't send a photo unless you are asked to.</tip>
            <content eid="2" prompt="Type your personal information here">
                <para>Name:		Pamela Janet Mason</para>
                <para>Address:	29 Greenlands Avenue, London, SW3 6RF</para>
                <para>Telephone:	01924 786512</para>
                <para>Mobile:		0779 9238182</para>
                <para>Email:		pam_mason@scapenet.com</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="3">Objective</name>
            <tip>TIP Some people do not include this section, but it does give an employer an idea of who you are.</tip>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="4" prompt="Type your objective here">
                <para>Objective:</para>
                <para>To find a role in a film or TV production company that will enable me to acquire and develop the skills required for a career in film or television.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="5">Profile</name>
            <tip>TIP Some people do not include this section, but it does give an employer an idea of who you are.</tip>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="6" prompt="Type your profile here">
                <para>Profile:</para>
                <para>An outgoing and articulate graduate with work experience in both television and teaching.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="7">Education and qualifications</name>
            <desc>Education and qualifications are put in reverse order. Add any prizes and awards that you have won.  </desc>
            <tip>TIP Omit details of your primary or elementary school. Try to give British equivalents of your qualifications.</tip>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="8" prompt="Type details of your education and qualifications here">
                <para>Education and qualifications:</para>
                <para>2009-present:	MA in Media Studies. Bristol University. Expected 2010</para>
                <para>2005-2009:	BA In Media Studies with French (2:1) Bristol University</para>
                <para>1997-2004	Beacon School, London</para>
                <para>3 A levels: Drama (A); French (A); German (B)</para>
                <para>5 AS levels</para>
                <para>9 GCSEs</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="9">Work experience</name>
            <desc>This is also  in reverse order, beginning with the most recent. You can include any holiday or part-time work.</desc>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="10" prompt="Type details of your work experience here">
                <para>Work experience:</para>
                <para>October 2007-June 2008: Language assistant in secondary school in France. Taught English to large classes and small groups. Ran a film club and a holiday dance and drama club. Assisted with school drama productions.</para>
                <para>September 2004-August 2005: Production assistant at Oordman and Associates Filmmakers, London N16. Performed office and on-set duties.</para>
                <para>June-September 2004: Tutor for Jacaranda Drama Workshops. Led groups of teenagers of different backgrounds in dance and drama activities. Directed end of course shows.</para>
                <para>July-August 2003: Host at Adventure Camping holiday campsite in France. Led the children's club for 4-10 year olds and performed various practical duties on the campsite.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="11">Skills</name>
            <desc>Your practical abilities. Include any exams you have passed or qualifications you have gained.</desc>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="12" prompt="Type details of your skills here">
                <para>Skills:</para>
                <para>Languages: French-near native-speaker fluency (CEF C1); German (B2).</para>
                <para>Good keyboard skills. Familiarity with Word, Excel and film editing packages.</para>
                <para>Clean driving licence.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="13">Interests</name>
            <tip>TIP Keep this short. Include a sport, a creative activity and a community activity, if you can. Avoid vague subjects such as 'reading' or 'travel' (unless you have done some serious travel for fairly long periods of time).</tip>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="14" prompt="Type details of your interests here">
                <para>Interests:</para>
                <para>Drama, both acting and directing; singing (was member of university choral society).</para>
                <para>Regular volunteer at a local centre for the homeless.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="15">References</name>
            <tip>TIP Give the names and addresses when you send your CV, either here or on a separate page.</tip>
            <content eid="16" prompt="Type your references here">
                <para>References:</para>
                <para>Professor May Duncan






                </para>
                <para>Department of French</para>
                <para>Bristol University</para>
                <para>Bristol BS8 1TH</para>
                <para>
                    <?xm-replace_text {para}?>
                </para>
                <para>Ms R J Oordman</para>
                <para>Oordman and Associates Filmmakers</para>
                <para>London N16 6TJ</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
