<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "Q:\rules\ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<framework>
    <framework_title> Reporting on data 1: graphs</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure this type of report.  There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your report.</para>
        <para>Remember that you can look the word up in the Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="What do graphs show?">
            <commentary>
                <para>Graphs can be used to compare many different things. Line graphs are usually used to show developments over a period of time.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is the report structured?" para_ids="5,6,13,14,24,25,35,36,46,47">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to create this report.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How was the report planned?" para_ids="2,3,5,6,7,13,14,15,24,25,26,35,36,37,46,47,48">
            <commentary>
                <para>In order to plan the report, the writer decides what to cover in each paragraph and takes notes.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Introducing trends" para_ids="2,3,13,14,51">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="52">Start with a general comment on the trends shown in the graph, plus the main trend.</para>
                <para showme="53">Provide supporting detail on the main trend.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Comparing trends" para_ids="2,3,24,25,54">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="55">Make a general comment.</para>
                <para showme="56">Give more detailed information.</para>
                <para showme="57">Compare these trends with other expenditure.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Contrasting trends" para_ids="2,3,35,36,58">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="59">Summarize the main contrast in the trends.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="3,8,16,27,38,49">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="9,10,11,17,18,19,20,21,22,28,29,30,31,32,33,39,40,41,42,43,44,50">The writer uses key words and phrases for reporting on data.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point>Examine the data you are reporting on and make notes.</point>
                <point help="datagraphs_ask_yourself.swf">Ask yourself questions about what the graph shows.</point>
                <point>Organize the information so that you highlight the main trends or features.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point>Use language that is plain and simple, but academic in style.</point>
                <point help="datagraphs_general_trends.swf">Use language to describe general trends.</point>
                <point help="datagraphs_developments.swf">Use language to describe developments over time.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point>Describe trends.</point>
                <point>Compare trends.</point>
                <point>Contrast trends.</point>
                <point>Summarize trends.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Have I introduced the subject of the data?</point>
                <point>Have I picked out the main trends in the information?</point>
                <point>Have I made some interesting comparisons between trends or figures?</point>
                <point>Have I reported the data accurately?</point>
                <point>Does the conclusion summarize the data?</point>
                <point>Have I answered the question?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar and spelling?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph eid="1">
            <name eid="2">Question</name>
            <content eid="3" prompt="Type your question here" image="oald8_wtdata.jpg">
                <para>Summarize the information in the graph by selecting and reporting the main features and make comparisons where relevant.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="4">
            <name eid="5">Introduction</name>
            <desc eid="6">Describe the subject of the data</desc>
            <notes eid="7">
                <para>Graph: proportion of total expenditure that UK households spent over 50 years on: housing; fuel, light and power; food; clothing and footwear; transport and vehicles. </para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="8" prompt="Type your introduction here">
                <para>The graph <useful type="key" eid="9">shows</useful> what <useful type="key" eid="10">proportion of</useful> their total expenditure households in the UK spent, <useful type="key" eid="11">over</useful> a fifty year period, in five different categories: housing; fuel, light and power; food; clothing and footwear; and transport and vehicles.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="12">
            <name eid="13">Trends</name>
            <desc eid="14">Make a general comment on the trends shown in the data and explain the main trend with supporting detail.</desc>
            <notes eid="15">
                <para>Expenditure changed in all categories. Food: biggest change, from 30% of total to 15%.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="16">
                <para>Between 1957 and 2007 expenditure in all five categories <useful type="key" eid="17">changed</useful> to some extent, but the most marked change was in the food category. At the beginning of the period the proportion of expenditure on food was <useful type="key" eid="18">more than three times as high as</useful> that in all the other categories, <useful type="key" eid="19">representing more than</useful> thirty per cent of <useful type="key" eid="20">total</useful> household expenditure.  However, by 2007 this figure had <useful type="key" eid="21">more than halved to around</useful> fifteen per cent, and was <useful type="key" eid="22">slightly less than</useful> expenditure on both housing and transport.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <content dup="16" eid="51">
                <para>
                    <extra_info eid="52">Between 1957 and 2007 expenditure in all five categories changed to some extent, but the most marked change was in the food category.</extra_info>
                    <extra_info eid="53">At the beginning of the period the proportion of expenditure on food was more than three times as high as that in all the other categories, representing more than thirty per cent of total household expenditure.  However, by 2007 this figure had more than halved to around fifteen per cent, and was slightly less than expenditure on both housing and transport.</extra_info>
                </para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="23">
            <name eid="24">Compare trends</name>
            <desc eid="25">Explain other similar trends and give details and compare these trends with others.</desc>
            <tip>TIP The number of paragraphs you use will depend on the amount of data you are writing about.</tip>
            <notes eid="26">
                <para>Clothing and footwear (10% - 5%) + fuel, light and power (6% - 3%) also fell. Less spent on these than other categories.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="27">
                <para>The two other areas where proportions of expenditure <useful type="key" eid="28">fell</useful> over the period are clothing and footwear, and fuel, light and power. However, the changes here were <useful type="key" eid="29">much less dramatic</useful>. Expenditure on <useful type="key" eid="30">the former dropped steadily</useful> from ten per cent to five per cent, and on <useful type="key" eid="31">the latter</useful> from six per cent to three per cent. For most of the fifty-year period, these categories used up a significantly <useful type="key" eid="32">smaller proportion of</useful> the household budget <useful type="key" eid="33">than</useful> the others.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <content eid="54" dup="27">
                <para>
                    <extra_info eid="55">The two other areas where proportions of expenditure fell over the period are clothing and footwear, and fuel, light and power.</extra_info> However, the changes here were much less dramatic. <extra_info eid="56">Expenditure on the former dropped steadily from ten per cent to five per cent, and on the latter from six per cent to three per cent.</extra_info>
                    <extra_info eid="57">For most of the fifty-year period, these categories used up a significantly smaller proportion of the household budget than the others.</extra_info>
                </para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="34">
            <name eid="35">Contrast trends</name>
            <desc eid="36">Give more detail on trends which show a different pattern
                and summarize the main contrast in the trends.
            </desc>
            <tip>TIP The number of paragraphs you use will depend on the amount of data you are writing about.</tip>
            <notes eid="37">
                <para>Transport + housing: expenditure approximately doubled: 8% - 16%; 9% - 19%.
                </para>
                <para>At the end of the period - most was spent on housing, least on fuel, light and power.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="38">
                <para>In two categories, transport  and housing, the proportions of expenditure <useful type="key" eid="39">almost doubled</useful>, <useful type="key" eid="40">rising from</useful> eight and nine per cent <useful type="key" eid="41">to</useful> sixteen and nineteen per cent <useful type="key" eid="42">respectively</useful>. Thus, by the end of the period, <useful type="key" eid="43">the highest</useful> proportion of household expenditure went on housing, and <useful type="key" eid="44">the lowest</useful> on fuel, light and power.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <content eid="58" dup="38">
                <para>In two categories, transport  and housing, the proportions of expenditure almost doubled, rising from eight and nine per cent to sixteen and nineteen per cent respectively. <extra_info eid="59">Thus, by the end of the period, the highest proportion of household expenditure went on housing, and the lowest on fuel, light and power.</extra_info></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph eid="45">
            <name eid="46">Conclusion</name>
            <desc eid="47">Summarize the report with a general conclusion.</desc>
            <notes eid="48">
                <para>Over 50 years, patterns of spending changed, proportion spent on food changing most.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="49" prompt="Type your conclusion here">
                <para>In conclusion,  <useful type="key" eid="50">the graph shows that</useful>  the patterns of spending in UK households changed to some extent over the period 1957 to 2007, the part of the budget spent on food showing the most marked change.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
