<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<framework>
    <framework_title>Article</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure this type of essay. There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your essay.</para>
        <para>Remember that you can look the word up in the Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="When might I need to discuss a picture or cartoon?">
            <commentary>
                <para>This task may occur in written or spoken examinations. Describing photographs or pictures can be similar to interpreting cartoons. There may not be a caption or any speech, but the photo can still have a message. You can also discuss the effect it has on you.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is the description and interpretation structured?" para_ids="1,2,5,6,9,10,13,14">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to create this description and interpretation.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How was it planned?" para_ids="1,2,3,5,6,7,9,10,11,13,14,15">
            <commentary>
                <para>In order to plan the piece of writing, the writer decides what to cover in each paragraph and takes notes.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Focus on the description" para_ids="1,2,4">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="i1">The writer begins with a general description.</para>
				<para showme="i2">The next three sentences add detail to the description.</para>
				<para showme="i3">The final sentence states what is said in the caption.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Focus on the interpretation" para_ids="5,6,8">
            <commentary>
                <para>Different techniques used by the artist to draw attention to important parts of the picture.</para>
				<para showme="i4">Technique 1—detail. Where?</para>
				<para showme="i5">Technique 2—emphasis. What is emphasized? How?</para>
				<para showme="i6">Technique 3—exaggeration. What is exaggerated?</para>
				<para showme="i7">Technique 4—symbolism. Which objects or people are symbols? What do they mean?</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Talking about the message" para_ids="9,10,12">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="i8">The writer notes the artist's use of irony.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Giving a personal reaction" para_ids="13,14,16">
            <commentary>
                <para>He/She then goes on to explain why.</para>
				<para showme="i9">The writer says that he/she agrees with the artist's message.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="17,18,19,20">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="i10">The writer uses key language for discussing pictures and cartoons.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point>Pick out the most important details of the cartoon/picture: What? Where? Who? What are they doing? What is happening?</point>
                <point>Identify techniques the artist uses to draw attention to important parts of the cartoon/picture (detail, emphasis, exaggeration, symbolism).</point>
                <point>Consider what the cartoon/picture is really about.</point>
				<point>Decide whether you agree or disagree with the message.</point>
				<point>Organize your notes into the framework.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point>Use prepositions (e.g. behind) to describe the cartoon/picture.</point>
                <point help="cartoon.swf">Use phrases to describe the cartoon/picture.</point>
                <point help="cartooncaption.swf">Use phrases to describe the cartoon/picture.</point>
				<point help="cartooninterpret.swf">Use phrases to describe the cartoon/picture.</point>
				<point help="cartoonmsg.swf">Use phrases to describe the cartoon/picture.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point>Try to avoid using short simple sentences e.g. 'In the centre is a man. He is shouting.' Use relative clauses instead e.g. 'In the centre is a man who is shouting.'</point>
                <point>Use a wide range of vocabulary. You can use your dictionary to find synonyms e.g. clearly/obviously; indicate/show.</point>
				<point help="personalreact.swf">Give your personal reaction.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Have I described the cartoon/picture in general and in detail?</point>
                <point>Have I given evidence and reasons for my interpretation?</point>
                <point>Have I talked about the message?</point>
                <point>Have I given reasons for my personal reaction?</point>
                <point>Have a started a new paragraph for each of the four sections?</point>
				<point>Is it the right length?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar, spelling and punctuation?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="1">Description</name>
			<desc eid="2">Describe what you can see in the picture or cartoon.</desc>
            <notes eid="3">
                <para>Bird's eye view of European city/town</para>
				<para>Factory, houses, vehicles, people</para>
				<para>In the foreground: recycling collection</para>
				<para>On the left: man putting bottle in recycling bin, being watched by managers from factory.</para>
				<para>Caption: ‘It is good to see people doing their bit for the environment!’</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="4" prompt="Type your description here" image="factory_cartoon.jpg">
                <para><extra_info eid="i1">The cartoon shows a bird’s-eye view of part of a European city or town. There is a large factory, several rows of houses, two vehicles and some people.</extra_info> <extra_info eid="i2">In the foreground, there is a rubbish collection truck, with two men collecting household waste for recycling. On the left of the cartoon, a man is putting a bottle in a street recycling bin. Watching him are two other men who are obviously managers in the local factory.</extra_info> <extra_info eid="i3">The caption reads ‘It is good to see people doing their bit for the environment!’</extra_info></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<content eid="17" dup="4">
				<para><extra_info eid="i10">The cartoon shows</extra_info> a bird’s-eye view of part of a European city or town. <extra_info eid="i10">There is</extra_info> a large factory, several rows of houses, two vehicles and some people. <extra_info eid="i10">In the foreground</extra_info>, there is a rubbish collection truck, with two men collecting household waste for recycling. <extra_info eid="i10">On the left of the cartoon</extra_info>, a man is putting a bottle in a street recycling bin. Watching him are two other men who are obviously managers in the local factory. <extra_info eid="i10">The caption reads</extra_info> ‘It is good to see people doing their bit for the environment!’</para>
			</content>
		</paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="5">Interpretation</name>
            <desc eid="6">Discuss the techniques that the artist uses to draw attention to important parts of the cartoon/picture.</desc>
            <notes eid="7">
                <para>Caption is what one factory manager is saying to the other. Attention drawn to them with detail and dark clothes.</para>
				<para>Size of factory exaggerated in relation to surrounding houses. Pollution exaggerated with black sky.</para>
				<para>Factory: symbol of industry in general; man recycling bottle: symbol of ordinary people—he has damaged the environment more by driving to drop off his recycling.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="8" prompt="Type your interpretation here">
                <para>The caption is clearly the words that one of the factory managers is saying to his colleague, because the focus of attention is on them and also on the man with the bottle: <extra_info eid="i4">all three of them are drawn in detail</extra_info> and <extra_info eid="i5">they also stand out because of the black clothing they are wearing</extra_info>.</para>
				<para>Another important element in the cartoon is the factory and the pollution from its chimneys. <extra_info eid="i6">The cartoonist has exaggerated the size of the factory in relation to the surrounding houses and has also exaggerated the pollution by blackening a wide expanse of sky</extra_info>. These aspects of the picture show the way that the pollution from the factory dominates the town and causes a serious environmental impact.</para>
				<para><extra_info eid="i7">The factory itself is a symbol representing industry in general</extra_info>. It seems that the man who is dropping off his one empty bottle in the recycling bin has driven there in his car, so he has probably damaged the environment more than if he had just thrown the bottle away. <extra_info eid="i7">He represents ordinary people</extra_info>.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<content eid="18">
                <para>The caption is clearly the words that one of the factory managers is saying to his colleague, because <extra_info eid="i10">the focus of attention</extra_info> is on them and also on the man with the bottle: all three of them are <extra_info eid="i10">drawn in detail</extra_info> and they also <extra_info eid="i10">stand out because of</extra_info> the black clothing they are wearing.</para>
				<para>Another <extra_info eid="i10">important element in the cartoon is</extra_info> the factory and the pollution from its chimneys. The cartoonist has exaggerated the size of the factory in relation to the surrounding houses and has also exaggerated the pollution by blackening a wide expanse of sky. <extra_info eid="i10">These aspects of the picture show</extra_info> the way that the pollution from the factory dominates the town and causes a serious environmental impact.</para>
				<para>The factory itself is <extra_info eid="i10">a symbol representing</extra_info> industry in genera. <extra_info eid="i10">It seems that</extra_info> the man who is dropping off his one empty bottle in the recycling bin has driven there in his car, so he has probably damaged the environment more than if he had just thrown the bottle away. He represents ordinary people.</para>
			</content>
		</paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="9">Message</name>
            <desc eid="10">What is the artist really trying to say in the cartoon/picture?</desc>
            <notes eid="11">
                <para>Cartoon is about our attitude to the environment.</para>
				<para>People focus on small-scale activities and ignore serious problems.</para>
				<para>Irony: contrasting what factory managers are saying with the serious pollution they are causing.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="12" prompt="Type the message here">
                <para>The cartoon is about our attitude to the environment. It is clear that the cartoonist is suggesting that while people focus on small-scale activities, such as recycling household waste, they are ignoring much more serious environmental problems such as the pollution from industries and from cars. <extra_info eid="i8">He/she uses irony to show that we are becoming complacent about saving the environment.</extra_info> This is done by contrasting what the factory managers are saying with what is really happening all around them: serious pollution that they themselves are responsible for.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<content eid="19">
                <para>The cartoon is about our attitude to the environment. It is clear that <extra_info eid="i10">the cartoonist is suggesting</extra_info> that while people focus on small-scale activities, such as recycling household waste, they are ignoring much more serious environmental problems such as the pollution from industries and from cars. He/she uses irony to show that we are becoming complacent about saving the environment. This is done by contrasting what the factory managers are saying with what is really happening all around them: serious pollution that they themselves are responsible for.</para>
			</content>
		</paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="13">Personal reaction</name>
            <desc eid="14">Do you agree or disagree with the message? Why?</desc>
            <notes eid="15">
                <para>Cartoonist is right. Many people recycle household waste but are complacent about pollution and need to address more important environmental damage.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="16" prompt="Type your reactions here">
                <para><extra_info eid="i9">Personally, I believe that the cartoonist is right.</extra_info> Many people are now very good about recycling their household waste. But, because we do this, we have become complacent about pollution and feel we are doing enough to protect the environment. We need also to address other more important sources of environmental damage.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<content eid="20">
                <para><extra_info eid="i10">Personally, I believe that the cartoonist is right.</extra_info> Many people are now very good about recycling their household waste. But, because we do this, we have become complacent about pollution and feel we are doing enough to protect the environment. We need also to address other more important sources of environmental damage.</para>
			</content>
		</paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
