<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<framework>
    <framework_title> An oral presentation</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure an oral presentation. There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your presentation.</para>
        <para>You can visit the help section to learn more about Oxford iWriter.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="How should I organize my talk?">
            <commentary>
                <para>There are many different ways you can organize your ideas and arguments in a presentation. Which you choose will depend partly on how long your talk is going to be but mainly on your topic. </para>
                <para>In many ways, preparing a talk is similar to preparing an essay—the talk needs to be organized and structured, with a beginning, a middle and an end.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is the presentation structured?" para_ids="1,2,4,5,7,8,14,15,17,18">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is the framework that was used to structure this presentation.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Introduction, overview and conclusion" para_ids="3,4,5,22,7,8,9,17,18,19">
            <commentary>
                <para>In this model the presenter has written out the introduction, overview and conclusion in full.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="The main part of the talk" para_ids="3,14,15,16">
            <commentary>
                <para>The presenter has made brief notes on the main part of the talk.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="3,22,9,16,19">
            <commentary>
                <para showme="6,10,11,12,13,20,21">The writer uses key words and phrases to guide the audience through the presentation.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point>Make sure that you prepare really well.</point>
                <point>Do your reading and research and make notes on the topic you are presenting.</point>
                <point>Think about the purpose of your talk: is it to inform, entertain or to persuade your audience.</point>
                <point>Think about your audience and how much they already know.</point>
                <point>Note that it is always best to speak from notes rather than reading out the full talk.</point>
                <point help="presentations_prep_for_quest.swf">Prepare for questions.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point help="present_approp_begin_end.swf">Use appropriate words and phrases to begin and end.</point>
                <point help="present_approp_structure.swf">Use appropriate words and phrases to structure your presentation.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point help="presentations_make_notes.swf">Make notes in English on cards.</point>
                <point>Write out any parts that you feel you need to, for example the introduction and conclusion.</point>
                <point>Write out and highlight key words and phrases to guide your audience through your talk.</point>
                <point help="presentations_prep_vis_aid.swf">Prepare visual aids.</point>
                <point help="pres_practise_your_talk.swf">Practise your talk.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Has my talk got a clear structure?</point>
                <point>Have I told them what I am going to say (Overview), said it (Main part) and told them what I have said (Conclusion)?</point>
                <point>Have I begun with a joke or surprising or interesting fact?</point>
                <point>Have I made good notes to speak from?</point>
                <point>Are my visual aids clear, large and easy to read?</point>
                <point>Have I practised enough?</point>
                <point>Am I sure that I can do the talk within the time allowed?</point>
                <point>Have I checked the pronunciation of any words I am not sure about?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary and grammar?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="1">Title</name>
            <desc eid="2">The title of your presentation.</desc>
            <content eid="3" prompt="Type your title here">
                <para><strong>The benefits of learning a foreign language.</strong></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="4">Greeting and introduction</name>
            <desc eid="5">Briefly state what your topic is.</desc>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="22" prompt="Type your introduction here">
                <para>Good morning.</para>
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="6">My talk today examines</useful> the benefits of learning a foreign language.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="7">Overview</name>
            <desc eid="8">Give a brief overview of the structure of your talk and how you will deal with the topic.</desc>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="9" prompt="Type your overview here">
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="10">I intend to outline</useful> three important benefits of learning another language:</para>
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="11">The first benefit I shall describe is</useful> practical—speaking another language means we can communicate with other nationalities.</para>
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="12">A further benefit is</useful> increased cultural understanding—when people can speak the same language, this breaks down barriers and bridges the gap between cultures.</para>
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="13">The final benefit that I shall describe is</useful> improved cognitive skills. Research shows that learning another language increases our brain power</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="14">Main part of the talk</name>
            <desc eid="15">This is the longest part. It should be clearly organized in a logical way.</desc>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="16" prompt="Type your outline of the talk here">
                <para>Elaborate on the 3 benefits mentioned in the overview.</para>
                <para>1. Practical uses for:</para>
                <para> Travel&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;.</para>
                <para> Work&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;.</para>
                <para> Study&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;.</para>
                <para> The Internet&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;&#x2026;.</para>
                <para>2. Increased cultural understanding</para>
                <para>3. Increased brain power</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="17">Conclusion</name>
            <desc eid="18">Summarize your points. Make any recommendations or suggestions for further work. Invite questions.</desc>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="19" prompt="Type your conclusion here">
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="20">In conclusion,</useful> I believe it is clear that there are huge benefits to be gained from learning a foreign language. I would even go so far as to say that it should be compulsory for all school children to learn at least one language for several years. The benefits that it will bring to them and society in general are too great to be ignored. I have never regretted the work I have put in to learning English.</para>
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="21">If anyone has any questions I would be very pleased to try to answer them.</useful>
                </para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
