<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE framework SYSTEM "ald8_iwriter.dtd">
<framework>
    <framework_title>A long report</framework_title>
    <framework_intro>
        <para>Below is a suggested framework to help you structure this type of report.  There are spaces for you to add your notes and the content of your report.</para>
        <para>Remember that you can look the word up in the Oxford Advanced Learner's Dictionary.</para>
        
    </framework_intro>
    <guided_tour>
        <step label="What is a report for?">
            <commentary>
                <para>A report describes a study, an investigation or a project. Its purpose is to provide recommendations or updates, and sometimes to persuade readers to accept an idea. It is written by a single person or a group who has investigated the issue. It is read by people who require the information.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How is the report structured?" para_ids="1,2,4,5,7,8,10,11,14,15,23,24,29,30,34,35">
            <commentary>
                <para>Below is a framework for creating long reports.</para>
                <para>The model you will see is an executive summary of a longer report so it does not include all of these sections.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="How was the report planned?" para_ids="1,2,3,10,11,12,14,15,16,23,24,25,29,30,31">
            <commentary>
                <para>In order to plan the report, the writer decides what to cover in each paragraph and takes notes.</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
        <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="3,13,17,26,32">
            <commentary>
                <para>The writer uses key words or phrases to:</para>
                <para showme="19">state objectives</para>
                <para showme="18,20,21,22">outline research</para>
                <para showme="27">present findings</para>
                <para showme="28,33">give conclusions and recommendations</para>
            </commentary>
        </step>
    </guided_tour>
    <practice_rubric>
        <planning>
            <checklist>
                <point>Do your research and gather all your information, including facts and figures.</point>
                <point>Organize your notes into the framework.</point>
                <point help="reports_ask_yourself.swf">Ask yourself questions about your readers.</point>
            </checklist>
        </planning>
        <vocab>
            <checklist>
                <point help="reports_lang_to_state.swf">Use language to state your objectives.</point>
                <point help="reports_lang_to_outline.swf">Use language to outline your research and present your findings.</point>
                <point help="reports_lang_to_give_conc.swf">Use language to give conclusions and recommendations.</point>
            </checklist>
        </vocab>
        <writing>
            <checklist>
                <point>Make your report as long as necessary but as short as possible.</point>
                <point>The main body of your report should be mainly factual and not based on opinion.</point>
            </checklist>
        </writing>
        <checking>
            <checklist>
                <point>Do I have all the sections I need?</point>
                <point>Does the title clearly show what the report is about?</point>
                <point>Does the contents list have the same headings and numbers as the report?</point>
                <point>Is the summary an accurate statement of the report?</point>
                <point>Does the introduction state the purpose of the report?</point>
                <point>Does the introduction say what the report will (and won't) cover?</point>
                <point>Does the introduction explain the research?</point>
                <point>Does the body of the report use headings and numbers?</point>
                <point>Would tables or diagrams to make the information clearer?</point>
                <point>Does the conclusion clearly give my opinion about the findings?</point>
                <point>Are my recommendations really based on my conclusion?</point>
                <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar and spelling?</point>
            </checklist>
        </checking>
    </practice_rubric>
    <paragraphs>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="1">Title</name>
            <desc eid="2">Your title should tell the reader what the report is about.</desc>
            <content eid="3" prompt="Type your title here">
                <para><strong>Web page design</strong></para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="4">Contents list</name>
            <desc eid="5">Use the same section headings or numbers as you do in the main part of the report.</desc>
            <content prompt="Type your contents list here" eid="6">
                <para>(Optional for shorter reports, not included in this model)</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="7">Summary</name>
            <desc eid="8">Include a summary of the purpose and objectives of the report, the kind of research you did, the main findings and conclusions and your recommendations, if any.</desc>
            <tip>TIP This is often called an executive summary. It follows the structure of the main report.</tip>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="9" prompt="Type your summary here">
                <para>(Optional for shorter reports, not included in this model.)</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="10">Introduction</name>
            <desc eid="11">Gives the background to why you are writing the report and explains what the report covers and what research you did.</desc>
            <notes eid="12">
                <para>Compare 2 web designs - see which people prefer.</para>
                <para>What attracts people and makes them buy products.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="13" prompt="Type your introduction here">
                <para>
                    <useful type="position" eid="19">The purpose of this report is</useful>  to compare two different web designs. The reason for this is to decide what kind of web page is most likely to attract new customers and to encourage existing customers to buy more products from us.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="14">Main body of report </name>
            <desc eid="15">Give precise information about your research and what you have found. </desc>
            <tip>TIP You can include tables and diagrams here, or these can be in an Appendix.</tip>
            <notes eid="16">
                <para>Asked 2 developers for different page designs - one simple (A), one more sophisticated (B).</para>
                <para>Research: 2 groups of 20 people (range of ages, professions, computer knowledge).</para>
                <para>Made 2 groups: one used A, one B, once a dayfor a month to do tasks: buying, getting info, returning goods, tracking.</para>
                <para>Also asked about technology for accessing Internet.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="17">
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="18">We asked</useful> two developers to produce alternative web pages for our company. We asked Developer A to produce a simple, easy-to-use design and we asked Developer B to produce a more sophisticated design with lots of eye-catching graphics. <useful type="key" eid="20">We conducted our research by</useful> asking a group of twenty existing customers and twenty non-customers to use the web page over a month. <useful type="key" eid="21">The group was made up of</useful> people with a range of ages, professions, incomes, and computer expertise. We divided the group in two and asked one sub-group to use Design A and the other to use Design B. We asked each sub-group to log on once a day and to use the web page to perform certain tasks, including: buying products, getting information, returning damaged products, and tracking deliveries. We also asked the sub-groups to assess how attractive they found their designs and whether they would be encouraged to return to the web page.</para>
                <para>
                    <useful type="key" eid="22">In addition, we researched</useful>the technology that people had available for accessing the Internet, including the devices people used and the connection speeds available.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="23">Conclusions/Findings</name>
            <desc eid="24">Give the facts you have discovered and your opinions on them.</desc>
            <notes eid="25">
                <para>People liked easy-to-use page (A) for buying. Don't want entertainment - Design B may be  slow to load, etc.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="26" prompt="Type your conclusions here">
                <para>
                    <useful type="presentation" eid="27">We found that, on the whole,</useful> people preferred to be able to purchase products quickly and easily. <useful type="structure" eid="28">In conclusion,</useful> users do not visit a site such as ours for entertainment, and while they initially enjoyed some of the aspects of Design B these could take a long time to load and users eventually became bored.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="29">Recommendations</name>
            <desc eid="30">Base these on your conclusions.</desc>
            <tip>TIP You can also predict what will happen if they are followed.</tip>
            <notes eid="31">
                <para>Adopt Design A (simple) with some features of B.</para>
            </notes>
            <content eid="32" prompt="Type your recommendations here">
                <para>
                    <useful type="structure" eid="33">We recommend that</useful> we adopt Design A with two or three of the more practical features from Design B.</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="34">Appendices</name>
            <desc eid="35">Give more detailed information here.</desc>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="36" prompt="Type your appendices here">
                <para>(Optional for shorter reports, not included in this model.)</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            <name eid="37">Bibliography</name>
            <desc eid="38">Give a list of any other publications you refer to in your report.</desc>
            <notes>
                <?xm-replace_text {notes}?>
            </notes>
            <content eid="39" prompt="Type your bibliography here">
                <para>(Optional for shorter reports, not included in this model.)</para>
            </content>
        </paragraph>
    </paragraphs>
</framework>
