<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Edited: 18 October 2013 11:22:08 by lead--><!--Edited: 18 October 2013 11:15:58 by lead--><!--Edited: 15 October 2013 15:38:21 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 15:27:34 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 15:20:26 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 13:10:52 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 13:08:44 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 09 October 2013 11:24:08 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 09 October 2013 11:02:18 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 09 October 2013 10:31:25 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 08 October 2013 14:30:53 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 08 October 2013 14:15:50 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 08 October 2013 14:00:21 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 15:15:06 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 12:20:03 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 11:49:42 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 30 September 2013 15:21:38 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 30 September 2013 15:20:08 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 September 2013 10:05:43 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 19 July 2013 14:16:24 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 19 July 2013 12:41:55 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 18 July 2013 10:29:04 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 15:21:12 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 15:17:16 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 15:11:47 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 July 2013 14:33:09 by coumbeb--><!--Edited: 09 July 2013 14:32:39 by coumbeb--><!--Edited: 09 July 2013 14:15:38 by coumbeb--><!--Edited: 09 July 2013 13:34:52 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 July 2013 13:20:33 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 July 2013 13:18:44 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 July 2013 13:14:59 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 08 July 2013 14:16:48 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 05 July 2013 10:42:06 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 05 July 2013 10:40:14 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 03 July 2013 09:59:52 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 02 July 2013 16:07:56 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 02 July 2013 15:45:54 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 June 2013 13:06:38 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 04 June 2013 14:58:32 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 04 June 2013 14:48:31 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 04 June 2013 14:25:58 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 16:26:52 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 16:07:48 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 14:39:21 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 14:00:34 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 10:14:35 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 April 2013 14:08:03 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 April 2013 12:31:14 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 08:36:51 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 07 February 2013 13:12:18 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 12 December 2012 10:14:23 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 12 December 2012 09:26:25 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 12 December 2012 09:16:36 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 12 December 2012 09:09:23 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 December 2012 15:54:53 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 December 2012 15:50:12 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 December 2012 15:48:11 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 07 December 2012 11:40:08 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 07 December 2012 11:36:44 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 07 December 2012 11:10:41 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 07 December 2012 11:08:25 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 07 December 2012 10:58:13 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 07 December 2012 10:49:54 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 06 December 2012 15:52:59 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 06 December 2012 15:51:29 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 06 December 2012 15:48:44 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 06 December 2012 15:33:34 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 06 December 2012 15:28:08 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 06 December 2012 14:18:16 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 06 December 2012 14:14:53 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 06 December 2012 12:38:14 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 05 December 2012 13:35:10 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 05 December 2012 13:31:10 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 05 December 2012 13:24:02 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 05 December 2012 13:07:00 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 05 December 2012 12:02:30 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 04 December 2012 16:05:49 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 04 December 2012 14:55:17 by duncanr--><framework>
   <framework_title>Writing a conclusion</framework_title>
   <framework_intro>
      <para>Here is a framework to help you write a conclusion effectively. This framework takes you through 4 moves, with advice on 2 more moves often used in applied fields.<br />There are spaces for you to add the content of your conclusion.</para>
   </framework_intro>
   <guided_tour>
      <step label="What is the purpose of a conclusion?">
         <commentary>
            <para>In the conclusion, writers stand back from their work in order to view it in the wider context of the discipline as a whole or the real-world situation. Thus, the purpose of the conclusion is in direct contrast to that of the introduction: it leads out from the narrow topic of the dissertation to more general issues. This framework shows you how to write an effective conclusion.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Why is it important?">
         <commentary>
            <para>In some disciplines, there may be some overlap between the Conclusion and the Discussion. For example, the final chapter may be called ‘Discussion and Conclusions’ or ‘General Discussion’. In this case, the conclusion may be a section of the final chapter. It is still important to include a conclusion, however, because it gives you the opportunity to highlight the most important points in your dissertation. The conclusion is the final impression that the examiners take away from your work, so it should finish on a positive note.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="How is it structured?" para_ids="6,7,13,34,35,63,64,68,69">
         <commentary>
            <para>The model text is an extract from a conclusion to a research article published in ‘Applied Linguistics’. The study analysed the language of academic weblogs (blogs).</para>
            <para>Here is the framework that was used to present this conclusion.</para>
            <para>Moves 5 and 6 are optional and are used in applied fields. They are not used in this model.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at the first paragraph" para_ids="6,7,8">
         <commentary>
            <para>The purpose of Move 1 is to summarize the findings of the work carried out.</para>
            <para></para>
            <para showme="9">Sentence 1 summarizes the work carried out.</para>
            <para showme="10">The rest of the paragraph highlights the most important findings.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at the second paragraph" para_ids="13,15">
         <commentary>
            <para>Move 2: Evaluation of the study</para>
            <para>In this model, the writer has mentioned two limitations of the study and has suggested new research possibilities that can follow from this.</para>
            <para showme="16,18">All studies have limitations, so the writer mentions what the dissertation has not been able to cover.</para>
            <para></para>
            <para>Move 3: Suggestions for future research</para>
            <para showme="17,19">The writer suggests some ways in which the study can lead to new research possibilities.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at the third paragraph" para_ids="34,35,36">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="37,38,39,40,41,42">Note that in this model, the writer combines the implications of the study with evaluation of the study.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="8,21,44">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="22,27,28">Negative evaluation signalling the limitations of the writer's research</para>
            <para showme="24,26,30,32">Positive evaluation of the future research</para>
            <para showme="45,47,48,49,50,51,53,54,56,57,59,60,61">Positive evaluation of the applications of the writer's research</para>
            <para showme="23,25,29,31,46,52,55,58">Modal verbs used to signal the future research and potential applications of the writer's research</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
   </guided_tour>
   <practice_rubric>
      <planning>
         <checklist>
            <point help="conclusion1.xml">In the conclusion, writers stand back from their work in order to view it in the wider context of the discipline as a whole or of the real-world situation. Thus, the purpose of the conclusion is in direct contrast to that of the introduction: it leads out from the narrow topic of the dissertation to more general issues.</point>
            <point>Think about what your dissertation has achieved: the most important ideas or findings that you want to the examiners to know.</point>
            <point help="conclusion2.xml">All studies have limitations, so think also about what your dissertation has not been able to cover.</point>
            <point help="conclusion3.xml">Use the four-move structure to help you write your conclusion.</point>
            <point help="conclusion4.xml">Applied fields have the option of adding Moves 5 and 6.</point>
            <point>Organize the points you want to make into the framework.</point>
         </checklist>
      </planning>
      <vocab>
         <checklist>
            <point help="academic_language5.xml">Use academic language.</point>
            <point help="conclusion5.xml">Language Bank: achievements and limitations</point>
            <point help="conclusion7.xml">Language Bank: future research</point>
         </checklist>
      </vocab>
      <writing>
         <checklist>
            <point help="conclusion6.xml">Grammar focus: use of tenses</point>
         </checklist>
      </writing>
      <checking>
         <checklist>
            <point>Have I summarized my work and highlighted the most important findings or results?</point>
            <point>Have I stated both the achievements and limitations of my work?</point>
            <point>Have I included a personal assessment of what I have learned in doing the dissertation, if asked to provide one?</point>
            <point>Have I assessed how far the aims of the study have been met?</point>
            <point>Have I made suggestions for future research?</point>
            <point>Have I placed the study in the wider context of research in the discipline?</point>
            <point>Have I used modal verbs to signal future research and possible applications?</point>
            <point>Have I used tenses appropriately?</point>
            <point>Have I quoted and referenced my sources accurately?</point>
            <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar, spelling and punctuation?</point>
         </checklist>
      </checking>
   </practice_rubric>
   <paragraphs>
      <paragraph eid="1">
         <name eid="2">Writing a Conclusion</name>
         <desc eid="3">How to write an effective conclusion to your work</desc>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="5">
         <name eid="6">Move 1: Summary of the findings</name>
         <desc eid="7">Restate briefly the work carried out, the aims, hypotheses or research questions.<br />Highlight the most important findings or results.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type your summary here." eid="8">
            <para prompt="Type your summary here." eid="8"><extra_info eid="9">This study has explored the manner in which academic blog participants define group relationships and create social meaning through interaction.</extra_info>
               <extra_info eid="10">The findings reveal that the academic weblogs in this study are social forums for self-presentation, networking, discussion, and idea testing, in many ways more similar to face-to-face academic discussions … than to written academic genres. The affective indicators … help to compensate for face-to-face affordances such as body language, facial expression or intonation. However, the specific features of weblogs (e.g. written medium, potential anonymity) also allow for the use of anti-social features more typical of some written genres in various disciplines.</extra_info>
            </para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="11">
         <desc eid="13">Move 2: Evaluation of the study<br />State what you consider to be the achievements and limitations of your work.<br />Assess how far the aims of your study have been satisfied.<br />Include a personal assessment of what you have learned from doing the dissertation, if you are asked to provide this.<br />Move 3: Suggestions for future research<br />Suggest how the work reported in the dissertation can lead to new research possibilities.</desc>
         <tip eid="14">TIP Suggestions for future research often follow from the limitations of the study.</tip>
         <content prompt="Type Moves 2 and 3 here." eid="15">
            <para prompt="Type Moves 2 and 3 here." eid="15">This study was intended to analyse some aspects of relational communication in academic blogs, but I am aware that<extra_info eid="16">it is limited in several key respects. First, although academic bloggers are quite a heterogeneous group</extra_info>, this study has treated them as a homogeneous group.<extra_info eid="17">Categorizing weblogs along several dimensions (e.g. participants' status, gender, motivation or discipline) could reveal significant results about relational communication ...</extra_info>Additionally, since previous research on academic discourse has revealed disciplinary differences in the use of some discourse strategies, a cross-disciplinary study of markers of relational behaviour in academic blogs could yield interesting results.<extra_info eid="18">Another limitation stems from the fact that data sampling procedures (restricting the number of comments taken from each posting) interfered with the collection of whole message threads.</extra_info>Since there are online discussions where disagreement escalates and exchanges get more heated,<extra_info eid="19">the analysis of whole discussions could yield a higher frequency of anti-social indicators. Future research could examine whole message threads in order to provide a more accurate picture of interaction patterns.</extra_info>
            </para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="20">
         <content prompt="Type Moves 2 and 3 here" eid="21" dup="15">
            <para prompt="Type Moves 2 and 3 here" eid="21" dup="15">This study was intended to analyse some aspects of relational communication in academic blogs, but I am aware that<useful type="collocation" eid="22">it is limited in several key respects</useful>. First, although academic bloggers are quite a heterogeneous group, this study has treated them as a homogeneous group. Categorizing weblogs along several dimensions (e.g. participants' status, gender, motivation or discipline)<useful type="position" eid="23">could</useful>
               <useful type="structure" eid="24">reveal significant results</useful>about relational communication ... Additionally, since previous research on academic discourse has revealed disciplinary differences in the use of some discourse strategies, a cross-disciplinary study of markers of relational behaviour in academic blogs<useful type="position" eid="25">could</useful>
               <useful type="structure" eid="26">yield interesting results</useful>.<useful type="collocation" eid="27">Another limitation stems from the fact that</useful>data sampling procedures (restricting the number of comments taken from each posting)<useful type="collocation" eid="28">interfered with</useful>the collection of whole message threads. Since there are online discussions where disagreement escalates and exchanges get more heated, the analysis of whole discussions<useful eid="29" type="position">could</useful>
               <useful type="structure" eid="30">yield a higher frequency of</useful>anti-social indicators. Future research<useful type="position" eid="31">could</useful>examine whole message threads in order to<useful type="structure" eid="32">provide a more accurate picture of</useful>interaction patterns.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="33">
         <name eid="34">Move 4: Implications of the study</name>
         <desc eid="35">Place the study in the wider context of research in the discipline and/or a situation in the real world, e.g. ‘Theoretical implications’ or ‘Pedagogical implications’.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type Move 4 here." eid="36">
            <para prompt="Type Move 4 here." eid="36"><extra_info eid="37">Despite the limitations</extra_info>,<extra_info eid="38">findings from the present study can help in understanding online academic literacy practices and developing research-informed pedagogical approaches to</extra_info>teaching such emerging practices.<extra_info eid="39">The results of this study may be useful in</extra_info>the preparation of materials intended to help postgraduate students and scholars participate effectively in online academic settings and make them aware of strategies to construct their authorial identity in such settings.<extra_info eid="40">The potential of academic blogs</extra_info>to engender solidarity and interaction revealed by this study<extra_info eid="41">could also be tapped</extra_info>in academic writing courses to help students discuss and revise a paper and foster in them a sense of community. In addition, … the results can help EAP students become familiar with the discursive features of informal scholarly genres, both digital (e.g. informal e-mails) and face-to-face.<extra_info eid="42">Finally, academic blogs can be used together with other genres … to help students acquire</extra_info>a repertoire of linguistic practices and associate these practices with specific genres.<br />(Adapted from Luzón, 2011.) For the full reference, click Help and select References.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="43">
         <content prompt="Type Move 4 here" eid="44" dup="36">
            <para prompt="Type Move 4 here" eid="44" dup="36">Despite the limitations, findings from the present study can help in understanding online academic literacy practices and<useful type="objective" eid="45">developing</useful>research-informed pedagogical approaches to teaching such emerging practices. The results of this study<useful type="position" eid="46">may</useful>be<useful type="objective" eid="47">useful in</useful>the preparation of materials intended<useful type="objective" eid="48">to help</useful>postgraduate students and scholars<useful type="objective" eid="49">participate effectively</useful>in online academic settings and<useful type="objective" eid="50">make them aware of</useful>strategies to construct their authorial identity in such settings. The potential of academic blogs to engender solidarity and interaction<useful type="objective" eid="51">revealed by this study</useful>
               <useful type="position" eid="52">could</useful>also be tapped in academic writing courses to<useful type="objective" eid="53">help</useful>students discuss and revise a paper and<useful type="objective" eid="54">foster in them a sense of community</useful>. In addition, … the results<useful type="position" eid="55">can</useful>
               <useful type="objective" eid="56">help</useful>EAP students<useful type="objective" eid="57">become familiar with</useful>the discursive features of informal scholarly genres, both digital (e.g. informal e-mails) and face-to-face. Finally, academic blogs<useful type="position" eid="58">can</useful>
               <useful type="objective" eid="59">be used</useful>together with other genres …<useful type="objective" eid="60">to help</useful>students<useful type="objective" eid="61">acquire</useful>a repertoire of linguistic practices and associate these practices with specific genres.<br />(Adapted from Luzón, 2011.) For the full reference, click Help and select References.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="62">
         <name eid="63">Move 5: Applications of the research (used in applied fields)</name>
         <desc eid="64">Indicate how the research may be practically useful in real-world situations.</desc>
         <tip eid="65">TIP This move may alternatively appear within Moves 1 or 3.</tip>
         <content prompt="Type Move 5 here." eid="66">
            <para prompt="Type Move 5 here." eid="66">‘Move 5: Applications of the research’ is not illustrated in the model text.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="67">
         <name eid="68">Move 6: Recommendations (used in applied fields)</name>
         <desc eid="69">Give specific suggestions for real-world actions to be taken on the basis of the research.</desc>
         <tip eid="70">TIP Where present, this move usually follows Move 5.</tip>
         <content prompt="Type Move 6 here." eid="71">
            <para prompt="Type Move 6 here." eid="71">‘Move 6: Recommendations’ is not illustrated in the model text.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
   </paragraphs>
</framework>
