<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Edited: 18 October 2013 11:00:28 by lead--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 15:35:35 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 14:34:57 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 11 October 2013 09:35:52 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 09 October 2013 10:09:28 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 08 October 2013 16:11:39 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 07 October 2013 11:55:12 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 15:02:17 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 12:14:05 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 11:39:54 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 03 October 2013 12:29:58 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 September 2013 10:17:34 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 September 2013 10:00:18 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 19 July 2013 14:24:28 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 18 July 2013 14:48:10 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 17 July 2013 11:55:38 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 July 2013 10:50:20 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 14:11:14 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 08 July 2013 12:42:23 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 05 July 2013 12:30:59 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 03 July 2013 13:33:11 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 03 July 2013 13:28:49 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 03 July 2013 13:27:23 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 02 July 2013 15:39:52 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 June 2013 14:53:52 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 04 June 2013 15:53:50 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 15:17:48 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 14:05:39 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 10:21:37 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 10:03:47 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 09:54:21 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 09:50:31 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 09:48:39 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 09:10:20 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 April 2013 12:33:32 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 19 March 2013 12:42:32 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 12 March 2013 08:51:46 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 12 March 2013 08:43:10 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 12 March 2013 08:40:37 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 11 March 2013 16:40:13 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 11 March 2013 16:39:21 by duncanr--><framework>
   <framework_title>Writing a Literature Review 2: social sciences</framework_title>
   <framework_intro>
      <para>This framework shows you how to write the literature review section of a dissertation or piece of research writing. There are spaces for you to add the content of your literature review.<br />Remember that you can double-click on any word to look it up in the dictionary.</para>
   </framework_intro>
   <guided_tour>
      <step label="What is a literature review?">
         <commentary>
            <para>A literature review is a section in a piece of research writing which describes the existing work that has been done on the writer's research topic and related areas.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="What is its purpose?">
         <commentary>
            <para>The purpose of the literature review is to set the new work in the context of what has already been done on the topic, showing the reader how the new research fits into the field and how it builds on and extends what is already known about the topic. By describing the research already done, the writer can point out what has not been done, or what is being challenged, and demonstrate the need for the new research. In this sense, the review helps accomplish the objectives (‘moves’ and ‘steps’) in the introduction. In fact, the literature review may be part of the introduction, although in some research texts—particularly dissertations—it may occupy a separate section.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="How is it organized?">
         <commentary>
            <para>Literature reviews are often organized according to a general-to-specific pattern, starting with claims about the research area in broad terms and moving on to specific areas, problems or unanswered questions within it.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="How is it structured?" para_ids="5,6,24,25,45,46">
         <commentary>
            <para>The Literature Review is often written in paragraphs which move from a general statement about the broad research topic, through gradually more specific aspects of the research. A gap in, or a problem with, the existing research is then shown, leading to a statement of the aim of the current study.</para>
            <para>Here are the opening paragraphs from a literature review included in a study of the relationship between income and happiness, published in the ‘Cambridge Journal of Regions, Economy and Society’. This model shows how to discuss and evaluate the literature, but it does not go as far as stating the aims of the current study. This would be in later paragraphs.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at Paragraph 1: older work" para_ids="5,6,7">
         <commentary>
            <para>In the first paragraph, older views are contrasted with the findings of more recent researchers:</para>
            <para showme="9">older views</para>
            <para showme="60,61">findings of more recent researchers</para>
            <para showme="8,10">language to show contrasts</para>
            <para></para>
            <para>Verbs appear in various forms: the past, the present perfect, and the present are very common.</para>
            <para>In this paragraph, the past tense is used for older research and the present perfect and present tenses for more recent work.</para>
            <para></para>
            <para showme="11,12,15">Notice how the text makes great use of integral references, where the name of the researcher or study is mentioned within the sentences. This is relatively common in the social sciences.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at Paragraph 2: summary " para_ids="24,25,26">
         <commentary>
            <para>The use of the present tense shows that ideas from earlier works are still considered to be current and relevant:</para>
            <para showme="27,28">Graham's argument is briefly summarized, using the present tense.</para>
            <para showme="29,30,31,33,57,34">Then, the works of other major authors are summarized, again using the present tense.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at Paragraph 3: main work" para_ids="45,46,47">
         <commentary>
            <para>The writer identifies a solid body of existing work. Past tenses are used as this is older work.</para>
            <para></para>
            <para>References can be integral or non-integral:</para>
            <para showme="48,49,51">integral references</para>
            <para showme="50">a non-integral reference</para>
            <para>More paragraphs would follow, leading to a statement of the aims of the present study.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="18,36,53">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="22,39,54">Reporting verbs relate to what the source said.</para>
            <para showme="20,38,42,56,58">Thinking verbs place the focus on the author's thought processes.</para>
            <para showme="19,21,37,41,43">Research verbs relate to the research that was done, including its aims, processes and results.</para>
            <para showme="40,55">Evaluative verbs indicate agreement with the researcher's findings.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
   </guided_tour>
   <practice_rubric>
      <planning>
         <checklist>
            <point help="lit_rev1.xml">Read widely, so that you are familiar with the existing research related to your topic.</point>
            <point help="lit_rev2.xml">Think about the purpose of your citations.</point>
            <point>Have a clear idea of how each area you raise in your literature review is connected to your own research.</point>
            <point>Show the relationships between works, e.g. that one builds upon another, or identifies problems with an earlier work, etc.</point>
            <point help="lit_rev_ss1.xml">Evaluate the works you are referring to.</point>
            <point>Use the review to show your reader the gap in, or the problem with, the existing literature which your work will fill.</point>
            <point help="writing_from_sources8.xml">Check the appropriate method of citation for your discipline. The model uses the author-date system.</point>
            <point help="lit_rev_ss2.xml">Remember that integral citations are relatively common in the social sciences.</point>
            <point help="lit_rev_ss3.xml">Make some notes and organize them into the plan.</point>
         </checklist>
      </planning>
      <vocab>
         <checklist>
            <point help="lit_rev_ss4.xml">Language Bank: literature review</point>
         </checklist>
      </vocab>
      <writing>
         <checklist>
            <point help="lit_rev_ss5.xml">Grammar Focus: tenses<br />A variety of verb forms is used in literature reviews, and the choice of verb form can help a writer create a particular effect.</point>
            <point help="lit_rev_ss6.xml">Grammar Focus: subjects</point>
         </checklist>
      </writing>
      <checking>
         <checklist>
            <point>Have I read widely enough on the existing research related to my topic?</point>
            <point>Have I shown how each area I raise in my literature review is connected to my own research?</point>
            <point>Have I shown the relationships between works?</point>
            <point>Have I shown the gap in the existing literature which my work will fill?</point>
            <point>Have I evaluated earlier research?</point>
            <point>Have I organized my review according to a general-to-specific pattern?</point>
            <point>Have I used appropriate tenses to refer to the literature?</point>
            <point>Have I used appropriate subjects of verbs (e.g. the research, the text or the researcher)?</point>
            <point>Have I quoted sources in the appropriate way for my field?</point>
         </checklist>
      </checking>
   </practice_rubric>
   <paragraphs>
      <paragraph eid="1">
         <name eid="2">Writing a Literature Review 2: social sciences</name>
         <desc eid="3">How to write an effective review of literature describing the existing work that has been done on the research topic</desc>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="4">
         <name eid="5">Paragraph 1</name>
         <desc eid="6">Begins with a broad idea and relates earlier works to each other.<br />Older views are contrasted with the findings of more recent researchers.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type Paragraph 1 here." eid="7">
            <para prompt="Type Paragraph 1 here." eid="7"><extra_info eid="8">While</extra_info>
               <extra_info eid="9">it was initially found</extra_info>that the relationship between income and happiness only holds within and not across countries—the so-called ‘Easterlin effect’—<extra_info eid="10">more recent econometric studies</extra_info>by<extra_info eid="11">Deaton (2008)</extra_info>and<extra_info eid="12">Stevenson and Wolfers (2008)</extra_info>based on new data collected worldwide by the Gallup Organization<extra_info eid="60">have challenged this view, finding that income exerts strong effects on happiness across the board</extra_info>.<extra_info eid="15">Sacks et al. (2010)</extra_info>
               <extra_info eid="61">suggest that there is a close relationship between material living standards and life satisfaction and that countries that experience a rapid economic growth also get an equivalent increase in life satisfaction levels</extra_info>.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="17">
         <content prompt="Type Paragraph 1 here." eid="18" dup="7">
            <para prompt="Type Paragraph 1 here." eid="18" dup="7">While it was initially<useful type="position" eid="19">found</useful>that the relationship between income and happiness only holds within and not across countries—the so-called ‘Easterlin effect’—more recent econometric studies by Deaton (2008) and Stevenson and Wolfers (2008) based on new data collected worldwide by the Gallup Organization have<useful type="structure" eid="20">challenged</useful>this view,<useful type="position" eid="21">finding</useful>that income exerts strong effects on happiness across the board. Sacks et al. (2010)<useful type="verbs" eid="22">suggest</useful>that there is a close relationship between material living standards and life satisfaction and that countries that experience a rapid economic growth also get an equivalent increase in life satisfaction levels.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="23">
         <name eid="24">Paragraph 2</name>
         <desc eid="25">Develops the ideas in the first paragraph further, summarizing important work.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type Paragraph 2 here." eid="26">
            <para prompt="Type Paragraph 2 here." eid="26">While income levels matter for happiness, work by Graham (2008)<extra_info eid="27">finds</extra_info>the relationship between the two is relative. Noting the paradox of the ‘happy peasant and the miserable millionaire’, Graham<extra_info eid="28">contends</extra_info>that although people can adapt to be happy at low levels of income, they are far less happy when there is uncertainty over their future wealth. Thus, the income effect on happiness is not only based on individual perceptions but also on the social and economic context in which individuals are embedded. The effects of unemployment on happiness tend to be larger in places where unemployment is generally low, while the effect is weaker if the individual lives in a place with high unemployment and thus the future is more uncertain. Helliwell (2003)<extra_info eid="29">suggests</extra_info>that happiness is affected by institutional factors such as governmental stability or effectiveness more so than economic ones. Helliwell and Putnam (2004)<extra_info eid="30">note</extra_info>[a] strong connection between social capital and happiness, beyond income effects. Deaton (2008)<extra_info eid="31">examines</extra_info>the relationship between income and life satisfaction and<extra_info eid="57">concludes</extra_info>that there is a strong relationship between the two. Deaton does, however,<extra_info eid="33">question</extra_info>the usefulness of health or health satisfaction as happiness measures, as he<extra_info eid="34">finds</extra_info>such measures have little relation with life satisfaction as a whole.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="35">
         <content prompt="Type Paragraph 2 here." eid="36" dup="26">
            <para prompt="Type Paragraph 2 here." eid="36" dup="26">While income levels matter for happiness, work by Graham (2008)<useful type="position" eid="37">finds</useful>the relationship between the two is relative. Noting the paradox of the ‘happy peasant and the miserable millionaire’, Graham<useful type="structure" eid="38">contends</useful>that although people can adapt to be happy at low levels of income, they are far less happy when there is uncertainty over their future wealth. Thus, the income effect on happiness is not only based on individual perceptions but also on the social and economic context in which individuals are embedded. The effects of unemployment on happiness tend to be larger in places where unemployment is generally low, while the effect is weaker if the individual lives in a place with high unemployment and thus the future is more uncertain. Helliwell (2003)<useful type="verbs" eid="39">suggests</useful>that happiness is affected by institutional factors such as governmental stability or effectiveness more so than economic ones. Helliwell and Putnam (2004)<useful type="objective" eid="40">note</useful>[a] strong connection between social capital and happiness, beyond income effects. Deaton (2008)<useful type="position" eid="41">examines</useful>the relationship between income and life satisfaction and<useful type="structure" eid="42">concludes</useful>that there is a strong relationship between the two. Deaton does, however,<useful type="structure" eid="58">question</useful>the usefulness of health or health satisfaction as happiness measures, as he<useful type="position" eid="43">finds</useful>such measures have little relation with life satisfaction as a whole.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="44">
         <name eid="45">Paragraph 3</name>
         <desc eid="46">Develops the findings of recent research further, identifying a solid body of existing work on the topic.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type Paragraph 3 here." eid="47">
            <para prompt="Type Paragraph 3 here." eid="47">There is a substantial literature documenting the transformation from industrial to post-industrial economies and societies. Nearly a half-century ago,<extra_info eid="48">Machlup (1962) identified</extra_info>the rise of the knowledge economy.<extra_info eid="49">Drucker (1967) coined</extra_info>the term ‘knowledge worker’ to refer to the emerging social group of workers who understand how to apply knowledge to productive use. This construct was later expanded to one of a ‘knowledge society’<extra_info eid="50">(Drucker, 1993)</extra_info>where the traditional means of production are replaced by human capital and new institutional structures.<extra_info eid="51">Bell (1973) predicted</extra_info>the rise of a ‘post-industrial society’ led by a class of highly educated scientists and technocrats. … [Two paragraphs follow (omitted here).]<br />(Mellander, Florida and Rentfrow, 2012) For the full reference, click Help and select References.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="52">
         <content prompt="Type Paragraph 3 here." eid="53" dup="47">
            <para prompt="Type Paragraph 3 here." eid="53" dup="47">There is a substantial literature<useful type="verbs" eid="54">documenting</useful>the transformation from industrial to post-industrial economies and societies. Nearly a half-century ago, Machlup (1962)<useful type="objective" eid="55">identified</useful>the rise of the knowledge economy. Drucker (1967) coined the term ‘knowledge worker’ to refer to the emerging social group of workers who understand how to apply knowledge to productive use. This construct was later expanded to one of a ‘knowledge society’ (Drucker, 1993) where the traditional means of production are replaced by human capital and new institutional structures. Bell (1973)<useful type="structure" eid="56">predicted</useful>the rise of a ‘post-industrial society’ led by a class of highly educated scientists and technocrats. … [Two paragraphs follow (omitted here).]<br />(Mellander, Florida and Rentfrow, 2012) For the full reference, click Help and select References.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
   </paragraphs>
</framework>
