<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Edited: 18 October 2013 11:09:34 by lead--><!--Edited: 14 October 2013 15:32:56 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 10 October 2013 10:17:05 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 08 October 2013 15:57:06 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 15:10:00 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 12:16:25 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 11:46:54 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 11:09:30 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 October 2013 10:57:37 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 03 October 2013 12:03:11 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 01 October 2013 12:27:24 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 25 September 2013 15:14:07 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 04 September 2013 10:18:33 by webbsu--><!--Edited: 19 July 2013 12:42:59 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 17 July 2013 12:43:01 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 10 July 2013 14:30:14 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 03 July 2013 14:43:43 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 02 July 2013 15:40:26 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 04 June 2013 13:21:39 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 15:33:21 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 16 April 2013 09:28:39 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 April 2013 12:34:51 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 April 2013 11:43:19 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 09 April 2013 11:35:21 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 14 February 2013 08:28:36 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 16:25:24 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 14:34:26 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 14:33:04 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 14:31:13 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 14:28:24 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 14:20:45 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 14:17:17 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 14:04:03 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 14:00:50 by duncanr--><!--Edited: 13 February 2013 13:56:40 by duncanr--><framework>
   <framework_title>Writing up Methods 2: a survey method</framework_title>
   <framework_intro>
      <para>Here is a framework to help you write up your survey method (after Lim, 2006). For the full reference, click Help and select References.<br />There are spaces for you to add the content of your method section.</para>
   </framework_intro>
   <guided_tour>
      <step label="What is a method section?">
         <commentary>
            <para>Reporting on the method used in undertaking your research is a crucial part of the research writing process. The method section is likely to be a detailed account of the steps undertaken in the research.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="What is its purpose?">
         <commentary>
            <para>Method sections in dissertations in any discipline will usually have a combination of three purposes. A method section aims to:</para>
            <para>1. describe the data and method used;</para>
            <para>2. explain how the data were collected and how the method(s) were employed in the research; and</para>
            <para>3. justify why the data were selected and why particular method(s) were chosen.</para>
            <para></para>
            <para>Method sections in different disciplines differ in terms of the emphasis they place on the different purposes. Humanities and social science disciplines tend to favour a more extended discussion of the explanations and justifications of how and why things were done. Whatever the discipline, the primary goal of the method section is to convey to the readers the validity of the research you have undertaken.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="What are its main features?">
         <commentary>
            <para>In social sciences, readers are likely to be as interested in your method as in your findings. This is particularly true of methods that involve a survey as there are a number of issues which need to be taken into account—for example, the sampling technique, the representativeness of the sample, the variables involved, and the questions posed in the survey.</para>
            <para>Almost all method sections using a non-experimental approach are likely to have the three main components of description, explanation, and justification of data and method.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="How is it structured?" para_ids="2,3,20,21,33,34">
         <commentary>
            <para>(After Lim, 2006)</para>
            <para>This is an extract from a method section in a research article published in ‘Social Science Japan Journal’, describing a survey of parental attitudes towards public school education in Tokyo.</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at section 1" para_ids="2,3,4">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="5">The writer explains the data collection method.</para>
            <para showme="6">The writer describes the method used (target profiling) by relating it to an existing method in the field.</para>
            <para showme="51">The writer explains how the method was used (target profiling in two stages).</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at section 2" para_ids="20,21,22">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="23,25">The writer describes the data (who they are, where they are located and how many there are).</para>
            <para showme="24">The author justifies the data (providing reasons for the exclusion of fathers and restriction to the Tokyo area).</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Look at section 3" para_ids="33,34,35">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="36,37,38,39">The author explains each variable and provides reasons for its inclusion.</para>
            <para showme="40">Then the writer explains how the results were calculated (the selection of responses to particular questions).</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
      <step label="Show me useful language" para_ids="8,27,42">
         <commentary>
            <para showme="14,17,44,45,46,48,49,50">Listing steps, variables or categories using numbers or letters is a useful way of presenting information.</para>
            <para showme="13,15,16,18,28,30,31,43,47">Verbs used to describe the research process</para>
            <para showme="10,12">Use ‘by + verb-ing’ to show how a particular result was achieved.</para>
            <para showme="9,11,29">Different ways of connecting your research to other research in the field</para>
         </commentary>
      </step>
   </guided_tour>
   <practice_rubric>
      <planning>
         <checklist>
            <point help="method_sur1.xml">Consider who is going to read your dissertation and what they will need to know about your research.</point>
            <point help="method_sur2.xml">Think about the data and data collection and what you need to say.</point>
            <point help="method_sur3.xml">Think about the method and what you need to say.</point>
            <point help="method_sur4.xml">Make some notes and organize them into the plan.</point>
         </checklist>
      </planning>
      <vocab>
         <checklist>
            <point help="method_exp5.xml">Use academic language that is concise.</point>
            <point help="method_exp6.xml">Use academic language that is formal and precise.</point>
            <point help="method_sur5.xml">Use academic language that is carefully structured.</point>
            <point help="method_sur6.xml">Language Bank: research verbs</point>
         </checklist>
      </vocab>
      <writing>
         <checklist>
            <point help="method_sur7.xml">Grammar Focus: first person pronoun</point>
         </checklist>
      </writing>
      <checking>
         <checklist>
            <point>Have I described the size, location and characteristics of my data?</point>
            <point>Have I explained and justified the data collection procedures?</point>
            <point>Have I described my chosen method in detail?</point>
            <point>Have I explained and justified my method?</point>
            <point>Have I used a selection of verbs to describe the research process?</point>
            <point>Have I used the first person and past or present tenses appropriately?</point>
            <point>Have I used ‘by + verb-ing’ to show how a particular result was achieved?</point>
            <point>Have I checked vocabulary, grammar, spelling and punctuation?</point>
         </checklist>
      </checking>
   </practice_rubric>
   <paragraphs>
      <paragraph>
         <name>Writing up Methods 2: a survey method</name>
         <desc>How to report on the method used in undertaking your research</desc>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="1">
         <name eid="2">Section 1: Description and explanation of the method</name>
         <desc eid="3">Explains the data collection method, describes the method used and explains how the method was used.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type Section 1 here." eid="4">
            <para prompt="Type Section 1 here." eid="4">2. Analytical Framework<br />2.1. Target Profiling<br />Our study differs significantly from previous research in its approach to categorizing parents. The typical approach is to group parents by a single characteristic, such as age or employment status, and then cross-tabulate with other variables.<extra_info eid="5">We forgo this method in order to create multidimensional profiles of parents that more closely approximate reality by taking several factors into account to develop a comprehensive and more true-to-life view of parents. For example, we do not lump all young parents into one group based on the single characteristic of age. Instead, we simultaneously consider several other factors such as parents' degree of cooperativeness, the strength of their sense of responsibility and whether their children attend cram schools.</extra_info>In short, we present a comprehensive narrative of parenting in Japan. …<br /><extra_info eid="6">When considering which methodology to apply, we were drawn to target profiling, a method used primarily in fields such as marketing science and psychology. In target profiling,[7] members of a sample are classified into several groups based on shared characteristics. The degree of divergence between groups is revealed by comparing their responses to a set of questions.[8]</extra_info><br /><extra_info eid="51">We conducted our target profiling in two main stages. First, using cluster analysis and attribute data compiled from parents, we categorized parents into several groups and uncovered the distinct characteristics of each group. Second, we assessed how much these groups differed from one another in their responses to questions on school education.</extra_info>
            </para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="7">
         <content prompt="Type Section 1 here." eid="8" dup="4">
            <para prompt="Type Section 1 here." eid="8" dup="4">2. Analytical Framework<br />2.1. Target Profiling<br /><useful type="position" eid="9">Our study differs significantly from previous research</useful>in its approach to categorizing parents. The typical approach is to group parents by a single characteristic, such as age or employment status, and then cross-tabulate with other variables. We forgo this method in order to create multidimensional profiles of parents that more closely approximate reality<useful type="objective" eid="10">by taking</useful>several factors into account to develop a comprehensive and more true-to-life view of parents. For example, we do not lump all young parents into one group based on the single characteristic of age. Instead, we simultaneously consider several other factors such as parents' degree of cooperativeness, the strength of their sense of responsibility and whether their children attend cram schools. In short, we present a comprehensive narrative of parenting in Japan. …<br />When considering which methodology to apply, we were drawn to target profiling,<useful type="position" eid="11">a method used primarily in fields such as marketing science and psychology</useful>. In target profiling,[7] members of a sample are classified into several groups based on shared characteristics. The degree of divergence between groups is revealed<useful type="objective" eid="12">by comparing</useful>their responses to a set of questions.[8]<br />We<useful type="structure" eid="13">conducted</useful>our target profiling in two main stages.<useful type="similarity" eid="14">First</useful>, using cluster analysis and attribute data<useful type="structure" eid="15">compiled</useful>from parents, we<useful type="structure" eid="16">categorized</useful>parents into several groups and uncovered the distinct characteristics of each group.<useful type="similarity" eid="17">Second</useful>, we<useful type="structure" eid="18">assessed</useful>how much these groups differed from one another in their responses to questions on school education.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="19">
         <name eid="20">Section 2: Description and justification of the data</name>
         <desc eid="21">Describes the data (who they are, where they are located and how many there are) and justifies the data.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type Section 2 here." eid="22">
            <para prompt="Type Section 2 here." eid="22"><extra_info eid="52">2.2. Subjects of Analysis</extra_info><br /><extra_info eid="23">For our sample, we selected mothers of second grade students attending public elementary schools in Tokyo, who had participated in the 2003 Benesse/Asahi Shinbun survey mentioned above.</extra_info>
               <extra_info eid="24">Although fathers and other legal guardians also sent in responses, roughly 90% of survey participants were mothers, so we focus solely on them. Given that younger mothers have been blamed for the burgeoning number of complaints filed against schools and teachers, we chose mothers of second graders in the expectation that they would be younger on average than the other mothers in the survey. Under the assumption that parents' concerns about middle school admission tests may further heighten their concerns regarding elementary school performance,[9] we further narrowed our focus to residents of Tokyo proper, where such admission tests are more prevalent, to control for this variation.</extra_info>
               <extra_info eid="25">After filtering out participants by these criteria and eliminating missing values, 116 mothers remained in our study.</extra_info>
            </para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="26">
         <content prompt="Type Section 2 here." eid="27" dup="22">
            <para prompt="Type Section 2 here." eid="27" dup="22">2.2. Subjects of Analysis<br />For our sample, we<useful type="structure" eid="28">selected</useful>mothers of second grade students attending public elementary schools in Tokyo, who had participated in<useful type="position" eid="29">the 2003 Benesse/Asahi Shinbun survey</useful>mentioned above. Although fathers and other legal guardians also sent in responses, roughly 90% of survey participants were mothers, so we focus solely on them. Given that younger mothers have been blamed for the burgeoning number of complaints filed against schools and teachers, we<useful type="structure" eid="30">chose</useful>mothers of second graders in the expectation that they would be younger on average than the other mothers in the survey. Under the assumption that parents' concerns about middle school admission tests may further heighten their concerns regarding elementary school performance,[9] we further<useful type="structure" eid="31">narrowed</useful>our focus to residents of Tokyo proper, where such admission tests are more prevalent, to control for this variation. After filtering out participants by these criteria and eliminating missing values, 116 mothers remained in our study.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="32">
         <name eid="33">Section 3: Explanation and justification of the method</name>
         <desc eid="34">Explains each variable and provides reasons for its inclusion.<br />Explains how the results were calculated.</desc>
         <content prompt="Type Section 3 here." eid="35">
            <para prompt="Type Section 3 here." eid="35"><extra_info eid="36">2.3. Variables</extra_info><br /><extra_info eid="37">We used eleven variables in our cluster analysis: age, employment ... access to information, tendency to worry, and cultural capital, for the following reasons[10]:</extra_info><br /><extra_info eid="38">1. Age. Included to test whether younger mothers are more likely to file complaints against schools.</extra_info><br /><extra_info eid="39">2. Employment. The amount of time a mother can spend with her child depends on her working status, and dual income (full-time) families presumably have higher incomes than those with mothers working part-time or not at all.</extra_info><br />[Nine further variables are presented with reasons for their inclusion (omitted here).]<br /><extra_info eid="40">To test the extent to which different types of parents have different attitudes toward schools, we selected responses to survey questions that focused on parents' expectations and level of satisfaction with their children's elementary schools.</extra_info>These questions generally fall into five categories (see Table 4 below for a detailed list of survey questions): (a) general expectations of schooling (e.g. what type of education and guidance should all schools provide?); (b) expectations of one's own child's school; … [Three further categories are listed (omitted here).]<br />(Yamashita and Okada, 2011) For the full reference, click Help and select References.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
      <paragraph eid="41">
         <content prompt="Type Section 3 here." eid="42" dup="35">
            <para prompt="Type Section 3 here." eid="42" dup="35">2.3. Variables<br />We<useful type="structure" eid="43">used</useful>
               <useful type="similarity" eid="44">eleven</useful>variables in our cluster analysis: age, employment ... access to information, tendency to worry, and cultural capital, for the following reasons[10]:<br /><useful type="similarity" eid="45">1.</useful>Age. Included to test whether younger mothers are more likely to file complaints against schools.<br /><useful type="similarity" eid="46">2.</useful>Employment. The amount of time a mother can spend with her child depends on her working status, and dual income (full-time) families presumably have higher incomes than those with mothers working part-time or not at all. [Nine further variables are presented with reasons for their inclusion (omitted here).]<br />To test the extent to which different types of parents have different attitudes toward schools, we<useful type="structure" eid="47">selected</useful>responses to survey questions that focused on parents' expectations and level of satisfaction with their children's elementary schools. These questions generally fall into<useful type="similarity" eid="48">five</useful>categories (see Table 4 below for a detailed list of survey questions):<useful type="similarity" eid="49">(a)</useful>general expectations of schooling (e.g. what type of education and guidance should all schools provide?);<useful type="similarity" eid="50">(b)</useful>expectations of one's own child's school; … [Three further categories are listed (omitted here).]<br />(Yamashita and Okada, 2011) For the full reference, click Help and select References.</para>
         </content>
      </paragraph>
   </paragraphs>
</framework>
